<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvelspring of wittie conceites containing, a methode, asvvell to speake, as to endight (aptly and eloquently of sundrie matters: as (also) see great varietie of pithy sentences, vertuous sayings, and right morall instructions ... Out of Italian, by W. Phist. student.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844261</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844261</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9054</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9054)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 204:14, 226:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvelspring of wittie conceites containing, a methode, asvvell to speake, as to endight (aptly and eloquently of sundrie matters: as (also) see great varietie of pithy sentences, vertuous sayings, and right morall instructions ... Out of Italian, by W. Phist. student.</title>
                  <author>Phiston, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27, 29-94, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Iones: dwelling at the signe of the Rose and the Crowne, neere Holburne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. Phist. = William Phiston.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vvelspring of wittie conceightes.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10925 on UMI microfilm reel 226.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 204 and at reel 226 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letter writing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVELSPRING of wittie Conceites: CONTAINING, A Methode, aſvvel to ſpeake, as to endight (aptly and eloquently of ſundrie Matters: as (alſo) ſee great varietie of pithy Sentences, vertuous ſayings, and right Morall Inſtructions: No leſſe pleaſaunt to be read, then profitable to be practiſed, either, in familiar ſpeech, or by writing, in Epiſtles and Letters.</p>
            <p>Out of Italian, by W. Phiſt. Student.</p>
            <q>Wiſedome, is like a thing fallen into the water, which no man can finde, except it be ſerched to the bottome.</q>
            <p>¶ AT LONDON, Printed by Richard Iones: dwelling at the Signe of the Roſe and the Crowne, néere Holburne Bridge. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Right worſhipfull, Maiſter<hi> Dauid Lewes, Doctor </hi>of the<hi> Ciuill Lawes, </hi>one of the<hi> Maiſters </hi>of her<hi> Maieſties </hi>Courte of<hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes, </hi>highe<hi> Iudge </hi>of the<hi> Admiraltie, </hi>and<hi> Maiſter </hi>of<hi> S. Katherins: R. I. </hi>wiſheth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall health both of body &amp; ſoule, increaſe of godly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this world, &amp; eternall felicitie in the Heauens, through Ieſus CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull Sir, it may ſeeme a point of great preſumption in me, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende into your protection, this ſmall booke, beeing another mans labour, and yet (notwithſtanding) the firſt fruites of my poore Preſſe, ſithens the comming in of this newe yeare: but theſe few thinges, being duely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, may (I truſt) deliuer me from the blemiſh and ſuſpect therof: One thing is, the abſence of the Author, who (not only) deliuered the Copye hereof vnto mee to be printed, but (alſo) committed the dedication of it to bee diſpoſed (by me) to my beſt liking: Another cauſe is, the wittie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighances, handled in the woike: but (principally) the heartie affection and duetifull good will, that I beare to your worſhip, with an (aſſured) hope, that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it in as good parte as my faithfull meaning is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you: For (ſometimes) a prettie Conceight, well contryued, may content a wiſe mans minde, no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:9054:3"/>a graue and great booke: Yea, (otherwhiles) a ſeely Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iet, applyed to good purpoſe, is not (onely) acceptable, but (alſo) commendable: A litle flower, if it haue a good ſcent, is worthie ſmelling: a litle ſtone, if it bee precious, and (therwithall) well ſet, deſerueth to be worne: a poore Pamphlet, if it tende to ſome good effect, may (haply) at ſome conuenient time, be worth the reading: I beſeech you (therfore) giue a poore Welwiller leaue to preſent your worſhip with this ſmall Collection out of dyuers notable workes, to the helpe and profit of many Engliſh Readers: &amp; not any thing hurtful to the learned, in other la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guages: and (although) the Phraſe do not (fully) ſatisfie the Curious, it will (I hope) ſufficiently delight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the wiſe: for the further contents whereof, I referre your worſhippe to the Authors Epiſtle, and then to the worke it ſelf: moſt humbly praying your worſhip to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſame into your protection and Patronage, as an infallible token of my good will towardes you, and to continue the iuſt defender thereof, againſt the ſcornefull crewe of MOMVS, his backbytinge Mates, to whome, all good thinges, are (continually) in contempt: And I ſhall (dayly) praye vnto God, for your worſhip, longe to continue in health, to the pleaſure of Almightie God, and the great deſire of all your Welwillers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your VVorſhips, moſt humble, to commaunde, Richarde Iones.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:3"/>
            <head>The Authors Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Conceites</hi> or <hi>Deuices</hi> of our mindes expreſſed, either with <hi>Pen,</hi> or by <hi>Speaking,</hi> do tende to this ende, namely, that they may <hi>Perſwade:</hi> And to <hi>Perſwade,</hi> is as much, as that one man ſhould make others beleeue, that our talke, or the thing whereof we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is either <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Falſe,</hi> and our <hi>Reaſonings</hi> or <hi>Speeches,</hi> be either <hi>publique,</hi> or <hi>priuat: Publique,</hi> are thoſe that are vſed vniuerſally to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, &amp; alſo, to thoſe that gouerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people: <hi>Priuat,</hi> bée ſutch as are vſed with <hi>Priuat</hi> Perſons, which bée aſſembled together, and they be of thrée ſortes: for they bée ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Thinges preſent,</hi> of <hi>Thinges paſſed,</hi> or of <hi>Thinges to come: Preſent,</hi> do comprehende <hi>Vertues,</hi> which are praiſed, or on the contrarie ſide <hi>Vices,</hi> which be blamed: <hi>Thinges paſt,</hi> as <hi>Manſlaughters, Rapines,</hi> and all the offences and debates, which are brought into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in which conſiſt to <hi>Accuſe</hi> and <hi>Defende: Thinges to come,</hi> are thoſe, in which we haue néede: firſt, of <hi>Counſell,</hi> afterwarde, <hi>of Election,</hi> or making choice. The firſt kinde, is called <hi>Demonſtratiue:</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Iudiciall:</hi> the third, <hi>Deliberatiue:</hi> all which (notwithſtanding) that they do chiefly reſpect publicke perſons, yet they be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily vſed toward priuat perſons, the which do many times giue counſell amongſt themſelues, doo <hi>Accuſe,</hi> doo <hi>Prayſe</hi> and <hi>Reprooue.</hi> Other ſortes of reaſoning, as to <hi>Reioyce,</hi> to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile,</hi> to <hi>Complaine,</hi> and all others bee reduced vnder ſome of the three aforenamed kindes, &amp; haue for their ende to <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade,</hi> the which is ſometimes brought to paſſe with reaſons either <hi>Probable</hi> or <hi>Apparent,</hi> and ſometimes with moouing mens affections: which things be principally giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature,
<pb facs="tcp:9054:4"/>and afterward ruled and fitted out with that wonderfull or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is ſhewed vs by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and by other, both aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and late excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Wryters, who through their rule and order obſerued, haue been the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the fruites of many Authors ſhall liue for euer: out of whome I haue taken ſome part of theſe <hi>Conceites</hi> or <hi>Deuices,</hi> which I haue vnderſtoode to be moſt learned, moſt méete, and proper to applye vnto all kindes and manners of <hi>Speaking,</hi> or of <hi>Writing</hi> familiarly, and thoſe that were moſt briefe, déeming that in the <hi>qualitie,</hi> and not in the <hi>Quantitie</hi> of wordes, and of <hi>Senſe,</hi> doth conſiſt the <hi>Elegancie</hi> of a commendable <hi>Speech,</hi> or <hi>Writing:</hi> and that heerby we may, in what <hi>Reaſoning</hi> ſoeuer it be, or in <hi>writing,</hi> receiue light of <hi>Inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and with ſuch <hi>Eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> adorne our matter, as ſhall containe fit <hi>Numbers,</hi> comely <hi>Figures, Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phores, Similitudes, Sentences, Aucthoritie,</hi> and <hi>Examples:</hi> as thoſe do ſhew foorth that I haue here placed in order: and to make ſerue with fewe, and with many, according, as ſhall be moſt conuenient, either in <hi>Writing,</hi> or in <hi>Speaking:</hi> &amp; becauſe one diſcours of <hi>Wordes,</hi> &amp; one <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>Epiſtle</hi> ſhall not haue occaſion to weaue together all theſe <hi>common places,</hi> it ſhall be expedient that they be of iudgement, and haue regard how to apply euery Sentence in his due place, according as <hi>Time</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Matter</hi> doth require, they which ſhall go about to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate any thing herein. Thoſe <hi>Sentences,</hi> which I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of <hi>Auncient</hi> and famous <hi>Authors,</hi> their names (for the moſt part) are coted in the Margent: others which haue béene partly the inuention of late Writers &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mine owne I haue not coted. Thus wiſhing for a frenedly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, in recompence of my frée goodwill, I ceaſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell in the Lorde.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:4"/>
            <head>The Wel-ſpring of Wittie Conceights, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Maner to expreſſe by word or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, how we reioyce, and what it is.</head>
               <p>TO reioyce, is a conceipte of the minde, that groweth of the pleaſure which we receiue of thoſe things that delight vs: like (as contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) to be ſory, groweth of the diſpleaſur that grieueth vs. And this Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt expreſſed in words, or in writting, is deuided into three ſpeciall ſortes, which be, the goodes of the Minde, of the Body, &amp; of Fortune: vnder which, are comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded many kindes of reioycing with others, of their conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and of proper and common words, apt vnto all ſortes of perſwading.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OF HEALTH.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you (moſt deare Frend <hi>M.N.</hi>) be in good health, I am as glad as I truſt you vnderſtande that I am.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I needed none other conſolation in this your abſence (for to moderate my griefe) then the aduertiſſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that you giue me of your good welfare.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> You, who knowe howe carefull I am of your he alth, I would that ye would more often let me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande of the ſame then you doe, except that ye go about by this meane to make me (more ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly) wiſh
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9054:5"/>therefore, and ſo that hereafter, I (as of a thing more deſired) ſhould eſteeme it double worthie the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, as in very deede at this tyme it hath happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with me.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> With ſmall paines, of body yee might ere this tyme haue relieued the troubleſome eſtate of my minde, beeing brought to paſſe through your abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: which (my comfort) is the newes that you haue ſent me, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning your good eſtate, in which ye are, and of the which I continually do reioyce.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> If you knowe, how that my cogitations were buſied about nothing els, after your departure, but in deſiring newes from you, ye ſhould vnderſtande, that my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation hath growen through the newes that I haue receiued of your health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of health recouered.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> FOraſmuch (as I heare no newes of you) I very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your malady is well ceaſed, in which opinion I do ſo delight mee, that I feele my ſelfe halfe diſcharged of that griefe, whereinto your diſeaſe had caſt mee.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Conſider you how greatly my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation hath beene in hearing the recouery of your health, for that I feeling my ſelfe at that tyme in very ill caſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſutch, wiſhed for newes, did not (onely) recouer my former eſtate againe, but me thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength (which I had loſte) returned or came to mee againe, double.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9054:5"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You, who doe knowe, that your commodities and conſolations, bee my commodities and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may alſo bee aſſured, that I could receiue no better (nor more deſired newes) then that which I receiued of your health.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> That you haue recouered the health (that yee had loſt) hath beene a thing (as ioyfull vnto mee) as the recouery of thinges being moſt precious, (when they were eſteemed to be vtterly loſt) was wont to be gotten againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Dignitie obtained.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Am glad (not onely) becauſe of your preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, but alſo for thoſe things that may bee looked for (of you) hereafter. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 2. Epiſt. Fa.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I doe inceſſantly ioy that your honeſt deſire is reduced to ſutch an ende, as your piety towardes yours and the loue towardes your Countrey, haue deſerued: And that the reputation, the which your ſingular loue and famous vertues haue gotten to your conſolation, hath made a ladder vnto <hi>G. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus,</hi> to the ſame degree. <note place="margin">Cic Lib. 15. Epiſt. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> In this (my ioy) I haue imbraced you with think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng on you, and haue kiſſed your Epiſtle, and doo as heartly reioyce as of mine owne matter. <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Epiſt. 11</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> What delight I haue taken, in vnderſtanding of our <hi>Brutus,</hi> his matter: you may more imagine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I can write. <note place="margin">Lib. 16. Epiſt. 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> If you know how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue neuer ceaſed for any man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, in being diſirous to do you ſeruice: you may alſo be aſſured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none ſhal now ſtay me in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9054:6"/>feeling the gladnes of the dignitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue gotten.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Albeit, that there was neuer any doubte but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you were likely to obtaine all manner, honours and dignities, that were wont to bee graunted to men of wiſedome and great valour: yet, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that you were made a Byſhop, I receiued thereby ſutch great conſolation, as was wont to bee receiued of good newes, being not looked for, nor thought on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> I ioy in all reſpects (for your ſake) like as good Seruaunts do, in wiſhing for the contentation &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of their maſters: Moreouer, for ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and accidentes as haue made this your felicitie appeare vnto the worlde greater, for that it is moſt euident that the ſame was appoincted afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande, by the moſt prudent Iudgement of our Lorde God, to be receiued of you to your great praiſe &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, commonly deſired of all men.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> I will not make any long diſcourſe of wordes in giuing an account to your moſt reuerend lordſhip, of the conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I receiued thorow your promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the dignitie of an Archbiſhop: ſithens it is ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with your profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, you haue alwaies byn able to pearce into the moſt ſecret part of my minde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of dignitie promiſed.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Haue taken a wonderfull contentation of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible hope, which you giue me of your conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet the more eaſily obtaine the ſame (for this were the ende of an Epicure) but becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your greatneſſe is of if ſelf deare vnto mee. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 3. Epiſt. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9054:6"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Concerning the preferment that your Lord and Maiſter hath promiſed you, I do alſo with you holde my ſelf greatly benefited: I did neuer make account that it would happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe to your eſtate, aſſoone as I ſaw that you were placed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of ſo good, ſo gentle and louing a Lorde: to whome doo me infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite commendations: I haue iuſt cauſe to reioyce with you of your good fortune: and that, ſo much the more, inaſmuch as in theſe our miſerable times, it is no ſmall thing to attaine to an honorable life. God graunt you your heartes deſire.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I ioy with you, that as it were in your firſt youth with the gate of Vertue, and with the companie of fortune, you haue beene called to ſuch a place, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of ripe years do with long ſtudy ſeeke to obtaine.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> If Fortune doe not ſtaye in the courſe of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but that it reache to the full ſcope, and to the prefixed height of your merits, I alſo hope to ſee this my gladnes grow to ſuch perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and your vertue to ſuch a degree, that neither the one nor the other of vs ſhall neede deſire any more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Goods gotten.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> YOu are glad of your good fortune, and doe ſaile in the quiet Sea of your delightes without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet on ground, or caſt on rockes, ſo God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie winde for euer.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> For, the prouiſion or furniture that you receiued of the King: I do moſt humbly thanke his Maieſtie, &amp; do account my ſelfe greatly bound to him therfore.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You, who vnderſtande howe much I loue you,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9054:7"/>may alſo conſider with your moſt wyſe iudgement of the ſatiſfying or well liking that I receiue of any your gaine and conſolation.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I reioyce greatly (rather for the wiſdome that you haue ſhewed in getting of goods) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goods themſelues, foraſmuch as to be wiſe, deſerueth more praiſe then to be rich: And for your richeſſe alſo I do receiue (as great conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) as is requiſit to my loue towardes your vertue and goodneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Inheritance gotten.</head>
                  <p>IN this notable pleaſure and conſolation, which I haue receiued concerning the inheritance that you haue gotten: I ſhould alſo wiſh for ſome excellent meane to make my ſelfe merry with you, if I dyd not vnderſtand how that I haue to deale with you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is with a moſt prudent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who with the quicknes of his wit, ſeeth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the middeſt of mens hartes.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> You, which know how greatly I was wont to reioyce at any of your commoditie, how litle ſoeuer it was, may alſo with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your rare iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſider what gladnes I haue receiued in my minde for thoſe ritches whereof ye ſo worthely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Heire.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods which ye inherite I am very glad, but not ſo that I haue not kept a place for ſuch ioy (as I truſt) I ſhall more gretly teele, by that more plentifull profit &amp; greater honor, in which hereafter your perſonage is like to ſucceede.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Albeit, that my reioycing with you for the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance graunted you freely, &amp; for the gifts of fortune
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9054:7"/>can not bee without iniurie of the opinion which I haue of your minde, the which is of it ſelfe ſo great &amp; high that it diſpiſeth all worldly dignities: yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as a man, and that moſt affectionate to you, I can not ceaſe reioycing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of friendſhip gotten.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THis muſt needes be eſteemed a great matter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in vs whom fortune hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioined familiarity, it doth alſo lyncke together with frendſhip. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 2. Epiſt. f. 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The mildnes and maners of <hi>M. N.</hi> (are ſuch) that like as I am very glad that you be entred into freendſhip with him, ſo I am ſory that all men haue not knowledge of him, that they all might reuerence him as a moſt worthie perſonage.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> This ſeemeth to me (onely) to be the true fruite of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life, that is to ſay: the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of vertuous freendſhip, as I know (aſſuredly) that your friendſhip with <hi>M.N.</hi> ſhall be.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I hope, that through the vertue and goodues of ſutch a Gentleman, you ſhall liue euer more &amp; more to your contentation &amp; liking, and bee comforted by his practiſe, and that I ſhall euery day reioyce more plentifully, as nowe I doe ioy for that I haue beene the cauſe of your friendſhip with him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of a Reconciliation.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THe pleaſure that I haue taken of your reconcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (with ſuch a Friende) is none otherwiſe to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the diſpleaſur &amp; griefe that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9054:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>were felt in the controuerſie that aroſe betwixt you &amp; him: but, I aſſured my ſelfe that this debate could not laſte long, as being grounded vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malicious perſwaſion of others: And this renewing of amitie, I doubt not, but that it ſhall waxe euery daye more ſtedfaſt then other, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertues of each of you.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I ſeele ſuch pleaſure of your reconciliation and agreement, made with <hi>M. N.</hi> that although I was grieued whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you were angry one with another: I knowe not now, whether I would that this ſaide altercation ſhould haue happened or not: for, if it had not byn ſo, I ſhould not haue taſted this preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, the which is infinite.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Concerning your reconcyling againe with <hi>M. N.</hi> I iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo is not your Enemie, muſt needs be very glad therof, becauſe that on him ſhal depend the reſt and quiet eſtate (not only of your ſelfe) but alſo of all your howſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Inaſmuch, as you are reconciled againe with your euemies at ſuch time as ye might haue put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the foile, you haue therwith alſo vanquiſhed that euill opinion, which naughtie diſpoſed people had of you, and haue eſtabliſhed that good opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that good men haue of your valiance and excellency of minde, wherof I doe ioye without ceaſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of being in a good opinion.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Delighte my ſelfe with this (that I ſuppoſe) you doe now vouchſafe to loue mee more then you did afore, &amp; that you keepe mee ſtill in memorie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as can abyde nothing but that which is excellent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9054:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>(except it bee I) whome you do freely permit a place there.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Abeit, that my conſcience doth aſſure and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie with me what account ye make of me, yet, I am greatly delighted, for that euery bodye may nowe eſteeme of me to bee ſutch a one, as I am by you, that is, by a moſt commendable man, reported to be.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Like, as I do not greatly regard or ſet to heart, though vngratious and infamous people ſpeake ill of me, ſo I feele great pleaſure and ioy when lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons do commende mee.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Thoſe Lordes and noble men (with whome I doe very often talke) haue a moſt honorable opinion of your goodnes and vertue, of which thing I reioyce with all my hearte.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I, hauing ſeene the honorable mention (which you make of mee in the letters that you did ſend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>R.</hi>) haue not onely beene pleaſed with the letters, but haue thought alſo the better of my ſelf for haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained ſuch a mans commendation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of returne from a Voyage.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> WHen as your Secretarie came to meet you, I would with theſe my dutyfull commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, the which I deliuered vnto hym by mouth, haue borne him Companie alſo with theſe fewe lynes, the which ſhall ſerue rather to ſalute you, &amp; to reioyce with you of your returne, then for to ſet foorth in any wyſe, the relation of my faithfull hearte, which thinge the ſayde Secretarie ſhall do for me.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Becauſe that the abſence of a Friend both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9054:9"/>monly make his preſence more deare: therfore, I am not able ſufficiently to expreſſe the conſolation that I haue receiued of your returne.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Looke, howe much more long and daungerous your voyage hath bene, ſo much great er is the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction wherwith I do ioy (together with you) for your happy returne.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I am glad for your ſake (not onely of your hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py &amp; ready returne out of ſo long a voyage, but alſo, for your quicke diſpatch that ye had in your publicke affaires: for, in the one is comprehended your great diligence: in the other is ſeene your prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in dwing your buſines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of returne out of Exile.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> WHat greater thing can (naturally) be giuen vnto men, then to euery man to haue Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his owne? they are vnto me ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, both for the tender loue I beare them, and for the excellency of their wit, that they be more deare then liſe it ſelfe: yet, I neuer felt ſo great conſolation in hauing gotten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as I do now proue in that, they be reſtored to me agaime. <note place="margin">Cr. pro Roſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Nothing was euer more delectable vnto any, then my Brother was vnto me: yet, I taſted not ſo mutch the ſweetneſſe thereof whileſt that I enioyed him, as I did afterward when I was bereft of him: But after that, yee had reſtored him againe to mee, &amp; mee vnto him: it is an incredible thing to ſpeake of the ioy, which I therof conceiued in my minde.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You be returned againe ſo glorious from your exile, and with ſo great praiſe in the opinions of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ye do (as it were) cauſe me alſo to wiſh my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9054:9"/>ſelfe dryuen out of the countrey, ſeeing that the hope of returning thither againe, in ſuch ſorte as you are returned, would counterpaiſe al the diſpleaſure and griefe that I could feele.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> You haue bene in exile, as it were in a fornace, (inaſmuch) as your vertue is therby become bright and ſhining, is purged from the ruſt of other mens Enuy, which kept the ſame ſecrete.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Like, as I haue beene one of thoſe whome yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> vniuſt exile did moſt highly diſpleaſe, ſo nowe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not ſtay for any body of the world to ioye in my ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for your honorable returne into the Countrey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Letters receiued.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> I haue receiued from you twoo Letters, of which, both the one &amp; the other were very welcome, like as a thing ſo curteous and, wiſhed for in it ſelle, muſt needes be.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> With my exceeding delight I haue receiued the letter that you did write laſtly vnto mee, by which I moſt ioyfully vnderſtood of your proſperous eſtate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If I ſeeme vnto you too importunate, for that I put you in minde euery howre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhould writeften vnto me, impute the fault therof to the loue which I beare you, the which being ſeaſoned with the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your wiſedome, doo cauſe that I feele an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pleaſure in reading your letters.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I haue receyued a moſt great conſolation by your letters, as being ſuch, as are ful of much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pleaſure, and paſſing the ordinarie forte, the which thing hath cauſed mee greatly to long for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9054:10"/>
                  <head>¶ Of Matrimonie.</head>
                  <p>Of ſo houeſt and honorable a Matrimony, I will not at this tyme vſe any circumſtaunce of duty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full congratulations, inaſmutch, as concerning my minde &amp; good will towardes you (I hope) yee bee out of doubte: yet, I will this lay, that I ioye as greatly at your profit as I doe of mine owne.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> You may be aſſured that God (who diſpoſeth &amp; ordereth all theſe things before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they come to paſſe) hath not without ſome great miſtery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed &amp; per fected this mariage, wherof I do (greatly) reioyce.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I iudge this moſt holy knot of wedlocke, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for men, that without it (I dare auouch) we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not obtaine perfect felicitie amongſt men.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Sithens that I am not able to expreſſe the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which I feele of this your matrimonie, wherby yee may promiſe vnto your ſelfe a quiet eſtate of all the remnaunt of your life, I therefore will referre it to the diſcretion of your iudgement, and to that true knowledge which ye haue of my loue towards you.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I am like to be the laſt, that ſhall ioy together with your excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of his moſt fortunate mariage, as being one of his ſimpleſt Seruaunts: but I ſhall hereby reape this commoditie more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others haue done, that (at the leaſt) the long tarying of duty may cauſe (this my reioycing) to come in ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and regarde: wheras, it ſhould aforetyme haue ben obſcured through the congratulations of many.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Child-birth.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> NOtwithſtanding, that euery forte of your ſelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie appeareth vnto me ſtrange, for that through your manyfold merits, I haue alwaies perſwaded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9054:10"/>my ſelf vnder your perſonage to obtaine by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Lorde God all manner good fortune, yet, I haue by this new Childbirth receiued an infinite conſolation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The happy childbirth of your good bed-fellow, hath made vs ſufficient demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what care y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord God keepeth of your pleaſures &amp; conſolations.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I ioy for this Childbirth not ſo much with you, as with all the reſidue of the world, ſeeing, that the young childe that is borne, beeing begotten by you, muſt of neceſſitie be alſo partaker of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and excellencie of vertues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in you: euen ſo, I pray God that the beames thereof may ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, and endure continually all that time of life, the which doth yet remaine vnto your ſucceſſion.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Concerning this moſt fortunate Childbirth of your conſorte or yokefellowe, I am greatly replete with gladneſſe (not onely with you) but together with the whole Cittie alſo, as hoping hereby to ſee your yeares prolonged in the perſon of this Childe: and ſo, that (both) I and they ſhall afterward ſee (in long continuance) the fruite that wee ſhall receiue through your vertue and valour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To wiſh or pray for:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>and (firſt) for Health.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I</hi> Pray God, that hee may make <hi>M.N.</hi> wel again: Do not you ſuffer him any more (to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage of his frends and your great diſpleaſure) to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I Would to God that with parte of the light of mine owne eyes, I myght ſatiffye the wante of your ſight, whiche thinge, I woulde as gladdely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9054:11"/>performe (if it were poſſible) as I do nowe ſpeake it.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I pray God that hee will vouchſafe to conſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> health of your body, but ſo as it may not bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the health of your minde, becauſe, that like as ſome venemous herbe (being of it ſelfe deadly) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is mingled with other thinges, doth make a hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome drincke, ſo the health of the bodye without the health of the minde, is hurtfull, wheras beeing aco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied therwith, it is very great helpe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I will pray inceſſantly vnto God, that he would maintaine ſtill (both) the health of your body, &amp; alſo of your minde: foraſmuch, as nothing is worſe, then a ſound body to dwell with a ſicke minde &amp; Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I pray God, that hee will conſerue the health &amp; noble eſtate of your lordſhip, which thing ſhall bee vnto me a ſufficient recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for that faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice which I haue done, and deſire to do therto.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I would, it might ſo happen, that God would graunt a ſpeedy ende to your maladies &amp; troubles, &amp; that he would vouchſafe me a beginning of beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and reſt, the which conſiſteth, and is vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in your health and welfare.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Our Lorde God, keepe and ſaue the perſon of your excellency or highneſſe with a greater felicitie and proſperitie, then it wiſheth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To pray for Dignitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> OH that it might pleaſe God, that that ſingular vertue and goodneſſe (which gliſtereth in you) may not ſtaye long without the companie of ſome degree and dignitie, conuenient therto.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I pray God, that like, as he gaue you the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Hercules</hi> (that is) power to beare, any great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9054:11"/>and heauy weight: So, hee alſo will illuminate the heart of this our Prince, to honor you with any good dignitie, which may bee comformable to the valour of your merites.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> That you be in ſo grent hope and credit in that Court, as I vnderſtande by all people there, that ye be, I do not much maruell therat, inaſmuch (as this) and a greater matter haue alwayes bene promiſed me, by your vertues: So, I pray, God bring to paſſe that thoſe houours and dignities, which aforetyme appeared to my ſight in your perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may bee ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of you as ye bee of them.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Might it ſo come to paſſe (that the thing I haue pronoſticated of your Perſon) might bee brought to ſuch an ende as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did foretell of his owne perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: who going one morning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, promiſed his Mother y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not returne home againe to his howle before he was created Biſhop, (which thing) he happyly performed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Proſperitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> WOuld to God, the diuine prouidence might ſo worke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame ſelicitie might abyde with your lordſhip, might bee ſtretched foorth to yours, might be ſo continued in your ſucceſſion through an entyre accompliſhing of that hope which the world hath conceiued by the glorious fortune, &amp; by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of your vertues, &amp; by your goodnes, vnto whom I am particulary moſt bound.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I recommende mee moſt duriefully vnto your lordeſhip, the which (for the reuerence that I beare therto) I wiſh that I may feele and know to be moſt fortunate.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9054:12"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I pray God, that he would deliuer you from all trauail and grief, ſo as with a more quiet minde ye may liue free vnto your ſelf, &amp; to your fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt which I may account my ſelfe one of the deareſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> With the good grace of your lordſhip, I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me infinite times, praying for the proſperous eſtate therof for euer to abide.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I haue been exceeding glad to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of your good proſperity, in which our lord God increaſe you, and exalte you dayly more &amp; more, the which your aduauncement can not bee in ſo great a happineſſe, but I ſhall ſtill deſire it to be greater.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I muſt now intreate you, that ye would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to keepe alwaies in your minde the great loue that I beare you, and wil alwaies beare vnto you: Our Lord God, make you the moſt ioyful woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liueth: like, as he hath made you the moſt curteous.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> I pray God, that he will giue you ſuch proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as yee deſire (that I alſo knowing your conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) may thereby continue moſt comforted, if it bee poſſible that a minde (beeing brought into ſutch an eſtate as mine is) may be capable of conſolation.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Sithens, that our fortune doth on euery ſide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſhine againe, God be thanked, and alſo by all meanes pleaſed, becauſe he bringeth it ſo to paſſe, rather through his goodnes and mercie, then for our deſert.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To pray for a benefite, or good turne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Pray for time which may bring occation, wherby (through the effects of experience) ye may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what is the greatnes of loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I beare you.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> God graunt that I may within ſhort ſpace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe my ſelf ſome other effect that may be better for your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9054:12"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I pray God, that hee will one daye inſpire your Maiſter, to giue you ſome condigne recompence for your long and diligent ſeruice.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> God ſo bring to paſſe, that one day your ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune may ceaſe, &amp; that my ſimple authoritie may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, to the end that I may by way of a reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence, and with ſome benefite, ſhew you the gratefulnes of my mind, &amp; how hartely your vertues be well liked of me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Libertie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Pray God, that he will grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs grace to be able to wade out of this ſeruitude, to the ende that we may not alwayes ſtand to the diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch as would vs no good.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Whenſoeuer any mention is made of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient liberties, that this Cittie had in time paſſed, it ſhameth it to think of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruitude wherin it is now.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Veryly, the bridle of ſeruitude, is a harde and greeuous thing to any man, but it is moſt grieuous to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bee yſſued out of the chaſte belly of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the which (I truſt) God will one daye reſtore vs againe, although not for our deſertes, yet becauſe he will not ſuffer any more ſuch tyrannie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> God be the reſtorer again of that liberty (which wicked men of a malicious purpoſe) haue taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you after the manner of wilde beaſtes, for a tyrant is none other but a cruell wilde beaſte, ſtyll beeing thirſtie after mans blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Peace.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> OVr lorde God graunt, that of this agreement may follow an vniuerſall quiet, by which we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſcended to peace, not without da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I pray God, that he will grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you the treaſure of peace, ſo as hereafter yee may lyue to the pleaſure
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9054:13"/>of God, ioy of your ſelfe, your friendes and kinſſolke, in perpetuall richeſſe, the which dooth conſiſt in the tranquilitie of the minde, ſoule, and Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Foraſmuch, as there is nothing more conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to a good man, nor more worthie to a good Cittizen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue peaceably: I pray God, that he will light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en your minde with theſe cyuill paſſions, and that he will pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in you ſuch peace and reſt, as euery one deſireth, and as ſewe do know how to procure.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I, as one diſirous of your eaſe (can not ceaſe) but ſtill wiſh you peace, and do pray vnto God that he will graunt you it ſpeedely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Not to be in an euill Opinion,</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> knowe very well your true vertue, and I would to God that like as ye be without fault, ſo that yee were alſo without ſuſpition.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I pray God, that this report, which is come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine eares, of you, doo not bring you into ſome ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter opinion, with others.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> God graunt, that for the bounty and faithfulnes of this man, he be not contrary wiſe dealt withal by them that with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> venim of their malice do not ceaſe to go about for to defile and peruerte the minde of that noble Lord, to make him beleeue that white is blacke, and blacke white.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How to aduertice, and what it is.</head>
               <p>TO aduertiſe, is a word that hath diuers ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for, it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to marke, that is, to take heed, to hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, to waite for, to obſerue, and to regarde: it is taken alſo for to apply, indeuour, and to haue care of ſome thing: like as is in this place of conceipts, it is applied: the which do ſerue to exhorte for a comformitie: and is vſed in the deliberatiue and iudiciall kinde.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9054:13"/>
                  <head>To aduertiſe one to worke warely.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He maner of your doyng that matter, ſeemeth doubtfull vnto vs (foraſmuch) as men will iugde therof, according to the ende. <note place="margin">Cic Lib. 1. Epiſt 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If that the matter might be taken in hand and proceede, according to the forme as we would haue it, euery body will call you wiſe and valyant: but if it bee hindred hereafter by any euill fortune, they will all then ſay, that ye were a vaine and ambitious perſon.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I tell you, that men will giue their iudgement, not ſo much of the counſaile &amp; deliberation that you ſhall haue taken in the matter, as of the ende that therto ſhall happen.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Wee ought not alwayes to walke one and the ſelfe ſame way, but to tende our courſe to one &amp; the ſame ende.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I pray God, that he will be mercifull and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to your councells, but much rather that hee will make you to ſhunne offences, and cauſe you to haue care of your quietnes, and of the good eſtate of your ſucceſſours. <note place="margin">Cic Lib. 4. Epiſt. 18.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Sithens that I haue ſhewed you my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t herein, it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth now in your power to reſolue your ſelfe in what ſorte ſhall be moſt agreeing with your wiſedome. Yee be come hither free and vnbownde, but beware that you departe not hence ſclaues and bondmen. <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Epiſt. 10</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> It is time for vs to open our eyes, for, when ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this people can finde occaſion they will neither be withdrawen by conſcience, nor yet, by ſhame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9054:14"/>doing vs hurt, &amp; they will laugh, vs ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to ſcorne.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> I wiſh, that in this matter yee would deal circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, &amp; that you would not pretermit or let paſſe any duty that might make you correſpondent to the expectation which this noble man hath conceiued of your intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, dexteritie, and integrity, doing you to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame is a great furtherau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to you, if in this (your beginning) he make a good report of you.<note place="margin">Pro R. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> You ought to bee very wary in dealing herein, according to the importaunce of the matter, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which (I am ſure) that yee ſhall well diſcerne, how, beſides the vertuous commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that you may thereby obtaine, the eſtate of my wealth, and honour doth theron leaue and depende.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> I would that aboue all aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (which I haue giuen you to worke, and doe your buſineſſe warily) ye ſhould take heede (eſpecially) that you doo not fall headlong into any ſuch ſinne, by which your luſt might ouercome reaſon, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you take heed of all ſuch euil affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as might peruert your vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Take heede that you deale ſo cunningly, in the matter, that (as much) as is poſſible the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of my deedes may liue, the which be yours.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> I put you in remembrance (not onely to deale warily) but alſo preuily in this matter, for it was wont to be ſayd, that no attempt can go ſo well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but the enemy thinketh that it wil be daſhed.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13 Antiſthenes,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in what ſort a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to ſeeke profit of the common wealth: Like, as at a fire (ſayd hee) which a man ſitting too neere, doth ſcortch himſelf, and being to farre of, ſuſtaineth cold.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> Like as to a good gouernour of a ſhip it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9054:14"/>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee know how to deale in the variablenes of windes &amp; wether, ſo it behooueth a man to frame himſelf ſomwhat, according to the diſpoſition of his Superiors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To beware of Errours.</head>
                  <p>IT is the parte of a wiſe man to foreſee all matters that may happen vnto him, and to beare ſuch hap as ſhall betyde him patiently, but it is a matter of a farre worthier counſell to prouide for ſuch things as may come to paſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> You muſt in this reſpect ponder with your ſelfe, not what I ſay, but what I ought and might ſay. <note place="margin">Pro Aulo Cluentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The yong men of great wit bee alwayes more ready to be holden within orderly boundes, then to be pricked forwarde with the courſe of glorie. <note place="margin">Pro. M. Celi</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Thoſe that be entred out of the deepe Sea into Harborow &amp; arriued at hauen, were wont to teach others diligently which go that way, how thei muſt take heede of the tempeſtes, of the ordering of their courſe, of the dangerous places, inaſmuch as by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wee are exhorted to fauour thoſe that enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame daungers, that we haue eſcaped. <note place="margin">Pro Luc. Murena.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 Conſider with your ſelfe, that if you know ye be not fit, by your own only induſtrie to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh this buſineſſe, it is better for you to procure ayde therin, which may ſupply in your imbecillitie, then that ye ſhould fall into any errours.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> If in theſe your affaires ye deale ſo as your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon bee not intermidled with luſtes or affections, I doubt not of any errour to remaine on your behalfe.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Ponder with your ſelf, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not beſt for you to innouate or deuiſe &amp; begin any new thing beſids my commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for to proue a new way, wheras the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9054:15"/>gaine is doubtefull, and the daunger certaine, is the parte of an vnwiſe man.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> I would not be ſlacke to aduertiſe you, although I want knowledge how to declare the aboundance of dutyfulnes and ſeruice that I owe you.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Way with your ſelf (that to ſatiſfie) the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of a particular man, is no hinderaunce to your vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall commoditie and honour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Traiterous dealings.</head>
                  <p>I Thought good to ſende vnto you in haſt by this <hi>Calfurnius</hi> my very familiar Freend, to the intent that you might aſſuredly vnderſtande, that I doe moſt hartely regarde your life and honour. <note place="margin">Cic. ad Attic.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Not onely your enemie, but alſo ſome that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted themſelues to be your freends, taking occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this your neceſſity, haue ſought meanes to bring you out of the peoples fauor, and haue ſo dealt, that what through the falſhood of the iudges and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of many others, they haue peruerted trueth, and not regarded your iuſt cauſe. <note place="margin">Lib. 1. Epiſt. 3</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You may not bee ſeduced in any wyſe by ſutch fellowes, nor yet giue credit to thoſe counſailes that they will giue you. <note place="margin">Lib. 2. Epiſt. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> If thou abydeſt at this ſtay, that thou deſireſt to liue more free, thou oughteſt not withſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that (as our chaunce may bee) none of vs all doth liue in any great ſafety. <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Epi. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> If thou ſhouldeſt giue a knife into the hand of a yong childe, or into the hande of one that is fainte, or feeble through age: Hee (ſutch a one with the force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) can do no great hurte to any man: yet, if ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> one ſhould thruſt it to the naked body of any man,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9054:15"/>though he were a very ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man, it might wounde him: Euen ſo, thoſe whom thou accounteſt moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of leaſt valour, if aduerſitie ſhould happen to leaue thee vnarmed and in miſerie, might be able to put thee to griefe. <note place="margin">Pro P. Seſtio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> A haynous thing is it for a man, to betraye ſuch a one as repoſeth confidence in him, and looke howe mutch greater eſtate a man is, ſo mutch leſſe ſafety can he put confydence in any: yet, it is requiſite that he put more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence: for (to be betrayed) is a thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more often happeneth to Kings and Princes, then to others.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> All things that be delectable, are not profitable, for often times that which is hurtfull, is pleaſaunt &amp; ſweete, and that which is commodious, is bitter.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Take heede aboue all thinges of betrayinges, forſomutch as the hatred, is vniuerſall, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at your elbowes ende, cauſeth that yee can not promiſe vnto your ſelfe any particular ſafetie.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> I do put you in minde, that ye looke rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about you, and conſider that with all due diligente ſpeede: you (being compaſſed about hardly with Freendes) may finde meanes to ariſe out of this trouble.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>01</hi> Be wary and circumſpect to haue an eye vnto betraying, for he that hath cauſe to feare euery man, cannot, neither ought he aſſure himſelfe of any.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Go to, take heede, as well as yee can howe you repoſe confidence in any body, before that you haue had tryal of him, leaſt that in time to come, ye repent your raſh putting of great confydence in hym, who deſerued but litle.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Like as the Wolfe is a beaſt like vnto a dogge,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9054:16"/>euen ſo a Flatterer, an Adulterer, and a Paraſite, is like vnto a Friende: Take you diligent heede there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that (in ſteed of truſty dogs) ye admit not wolfs to the keeping of your flocke. <note place="margin">Epiteti,</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Enemitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> TAke as good heed as ye can that you foſter not enemitie neere your ſelfe: for, as long as men ſhall liue vppon earth, ſo longe will Enemies remaine.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Ye muſt be very circumſpect, leaſt in the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of your dignitie, your enemies do alſo increaſe: for (vndoubtedly) looke how faſt the one groweth, ſo likewiſe will the others (either publickly or priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) increaſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Thou oughteſt three manner of wayes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the qualitie of hym, with whome thou art co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant (that is) whither hee be thy ſuperiour, thine inferiour, or thine equall: If he be thy Superiour, thou muſt giue him hearing and ſooth him: If hee be thine Inferiour, thou muſt perſwade him with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie &amp; mildnes: and if he be thine equall, thou muſt accorde with him. So doing, thou ſhalt not fall into enemitie and hatred. <note place="margin">Epiteti.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Like (as he) that is delighted in bodyly exerciſe, muſt beware of wrinches and diſordered falles, ſo he that glorieth of his good fortune, muſt ſhun enuy. <note place="margin">Ariſtone.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> All diligence muſt be applyed, that you may be more reuerenced then feared, for that, the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of grauitie, and the other, of inhumanitie.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Euen, as he, that walketh in the Sun-ſhine, is accompanied with a ſhadowe, ſo hee that walketh through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> path of glory, hath for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemitie <note place="margin">Ariſtone.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:9054:16"/>
                  <head>¶ Not to fall in an euill Opinion.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IT is a great alluring to make vs fall vnto wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, when as wee vnderſtande or thinke that we ſhall not be puniſhed therfore. <note place="margin">Cic. Pro. Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> It is one thing to talke wiſely, another thinge to liue therafter: one thing to bee accounted wiſe, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to bee ſo indeede.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Anger, Pride, Crueltie, Wrath, and madnes be the companions of victorie: but enemies bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querours, whom many valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Captains haue luſtely vanquiſhed.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Do your ſelfe no iniurie, concerning the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that is had of you): that is, that yee bee ſuch a one as can not be vanquiſhed, nor yet bee deceiued: the one of which ſhall bee yours, and the gift of fortune, the other ſhall only be attributed to your wiſedome.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Take this aduertiſement as of a Freend, &amp; ſuch a one as loueth you, &amp; wiſheth you well, not of your enemie &amp; one that meaneth you harme: for (if yee doo otherwiſe) you ſhall giue me occaſion to thinke that flattery is dearer to you, then frendſhip.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> You (remember howe that for to haue the loue of all men vniuerſally, and the fauor of ſome noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men particularly) wee haue no ſurer waye, then to thinke how we may deſerue the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> There is nothing ſo hurtfull as an ill reporte, for, after that, thou ſhalt haue beguiled any one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily with falſe perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, hatred awaketh &amp; hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the innocent. <note place="margin">Cleanthus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Suſpicions do breed moe ill reportes, then doe the deedes themſelues. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Ye muſt beware of euill reports, allhough they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9054:17"/>be falſe, for moſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (being not capable of the trueth) do follow opinions. <note place="margin">Iſocratee.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> It behooueth you to be very carefull (rather to leaue behinde you a good reporte) then great ſtore of richeſſe to your Children, foraſmutrh, as the one is mortall, the other, euerlaſting: and with good fame, men may get richeſſe: but with riches, a good name can neuer be obtained.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Many men (haue often times receiued greater hurt by reproche) then by Enemies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Not to ſpeake amiſſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Would, that thou ſhouldeſt principallye haue this aduertiſement imprinted in thy minde, that thou keepe thy ſelfe eſteemed for ſuch a one as thou art, ſo that like as thou art farre from the filthines of ſutch actes, ſo thou mighteſt bee farre from ſpaking thereof. <note place="margin">Cic pro M. Ceſſio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Like, as it is filthie &amp; vncumly to write of ſutch things as be not conuenient, euen ſo) it is vndecent to name the ſame. <note place="margin">Pro R. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>do.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> A ſword in a mad mans hand, may well be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to an eloquent man without wiſdome: for as to the one, it ſhould be commodious if he were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, ſhould it bee to him, that he were without eloquence.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Take heede, that ye be circumſpect in talke, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that ouermutch raſhnes in ſpeaking, was wont to bring many hurtes.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> If thou ſhalt ſpeake amiſſe of our matter, thou ſhalt not ſpeake againſt vs, but againſt Iuſtice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the nature of the matter, contrarie to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, and the opinion of the whole worlde.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9054:17"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Bee circumſpect and warye in talking, rather applying too much modeſtie, then too much libertie: for, there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a crooked diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which can not be pleaſed with the humanitie of wordes.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> In opening the mouth of a wiſe man, like as in opening the temple of his ſoule, do appeare what heauenly riches, and vertues be reſident in him. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> If thou couet to haue diligent eare giuen to thy wordes, learne then to ſpeake well, and after that thou haſt learned ſo to doo, labour to make thy deeds correſpondent to thy words: in ſo doing, thou ſhalt get thee a good report. <note place="margin">Epit.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Simonides,</hi> was wont to ſay, that hee neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him to haue holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his peace: but oftentimes for that he had ſpoken. <note place="margin">Cleanthus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Xenocrates,</hi> aſſigning all parts of the day vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome buſines, appointed alſo vnto ſilence the due part: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which time he diſcuſſed priuatly with him ſelfe, what manner he ought to keepe in ſpeaking.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 Hippias</hi> ſaid, that it was greatly amiſſe, that he had not determined a puniſhment for Slanderers, as well, as he had for Theeues: Inaſmuch, as they ſteale awaye freendſhip, the which exceedeth all ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of the worlde. <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Albeit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backbyting hath power to confirme (in ſome reſpect) the opinion of them that giue eare therto: yet in proceſſe of time there is nothing more feeble then it. <note place="margin">Demoſt.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To be circumſpect in writing.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IT is no point of true wiſdome to ſee thoſe things that bee preſent, but to iudge of thinges to come a long time after. <note place="margin">Terut. in adelph.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9054:18"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> As your Letters were read with diligence, ſo they haue alſo beene well vnderſtood, I thinke that (according to your meaning) there is no ſentence in it but I vnderſtande it well. I ſhall bee very glad if you continue in your wonted warineſſe of writing for a good conſideration.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Way diligently with your ſelf, that no man can bee ſo circumſpect, who in this daungerous tyme of moſt wicked men can eſcape, but that ſome (whiche beare a frendly countenance) will eſpye out and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraye other mens ſecretes, for to put them out of fauour with this and that noble man, by diſhoneſt meanes.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Aboue all things (I for your benefit) do put you in minde that yee bee circumſpecte in wryting, and alſo that you ſo deale as I may haue no cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent mee for your ſake, of a thing that I neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Bee warie, and as circumſpect in writing as ye can, for (at this preſent) the commoditie of printing hath cauſed, that men are growen to ſuch a paſſe, as many will comment, vppon, not (onely) writings, and wordes, but alſo the thoughtes and ſecretes of a mans minde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To know himſelfe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> HE, that will make profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gouerne a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, it behooueth him principally to knowe howe to gouerne himſelfe. <note place="margin">Cic f. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If hee will liue after ſuch a ſort as good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do liue, it is neceſſary that he learne, and forget ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges, and ech of theſe thinges is very difficult for one of his age to doo. <note place="margin">Pro P. Quentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9054:18"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It was wont to be ſayde, that hee is moſt wiſe, who hath reaſon to diſcerne what is expedient for to doe, and the wiſeſt next vnto him is he that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to ſuch a man of moſt perfect wiſedome. <note place="margin">Pro Aulo Cluentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Phillip,</hi> King of <hi>Macedonie,</hi> after that he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many victories againſt the <hi>Graecians,</hi> becauſe he might not waxe prowde therefore, ordeined, that euery daye after in the morning, he ſhould be put in minde by a certaine young Childe, that he was but a man. <note place="margin">Elianus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Heraclitus,</hi> beeing a young man, and exceeding wiſe, ſayd, that he knewe noching. <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Demonicus,</hi> being demaunded, when he began to be a Philoſopher: at ſuch time (ſayd hee) as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon to know my ſelfe. <note place="margin">Biantes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> A certaine man demaunding of <hi>Chilo,</hi> what was the hardeſt thing of all? aunſwered, to knowe himſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Amongeſt the moſt principall thinges that are giuen men in this life, is, that the greateſt of them, (being giuen ouer to follie) ſome may applye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be wiſe. <note place="margin">Ariſto.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Diogenes</hi> ſaid, that thoſe men, which talke wel and do not knowe themſelues, be like ſuch Harpes, as haue a pleaſaunt ſound, and are ſenceleſſe. <note place="margin">Demoſt.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To adminiſter Iuſtice,</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> MEn doo become worſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of ſinning. He that gouerneth muſt not bee mindful of enemitie paſſed, for, it is not ſeemely for a gouernor, to be his own reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger neither muſt he be mooued at the inſtance of others,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9054:19"/>but by meere iuſtice. <note place="margin">Ter. in. Heant.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The iudges ought to put on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame minds, that the Lawgiuers did vſe in making the lawes. <note place="margin">Liſias.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Byon</hi> ſayd, that it behooueth a good Judge to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from his office with more gaine of good fame, then of richeſſe. <note place="margin">Solon.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Agatho</hi> ſayd, that a Prince muſt imprinte three things in his memorie: The firſt is, that he beareth, rule ouer men: ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, that he rule according to law: &amp; thirdly, that his Empyre is not his owne, neither laſteth euer. <note place="margin">Iſeus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Thoſe that puniſh the wicked, doe defende the good from iniuries.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> In <hi>Thebe,</hi> the Images of Iudges were made without handes, and with their eyes deepe in their heades, becauſe that iuſtice ought not bee corrupted with giftes, or regarde the countenance of men. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> A man that is in aucthoritie, ought excell other men, not onely in gouernement, and commaunding, but alſo in worthines and prudence. <note place="margin">Euſebius.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To conſerue and maintaine health.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> FOr the loue of God, ſet no worldly thing at this time more to heart, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of health, where with ye may the better doe ſeruice to the King, pleaſure your ſelfe and your freendes.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The change that is wrought by litle and litle, is an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that nature is plyable according to the mutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of tyme, which thing is ſhewed vs by God himſelfe, who doth not cauſe vs to paſſe on a ſodain from winter to Sommer, ſetting between them the ſpring time and Autumne. <note place="margin">Xenophon.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Your eating, drinking, ſleeping, &amp;c. would bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9054:19"/>temperat for the conſeruation of health.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> That order of liuing which many doe vſe, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to nothing els, but to weaken the body, and to make it ſubiect to euery danger, and to make feeble the vnderſtanding. <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> The health of the bodye requireth neither ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraboundance, nor want of any foode or pleaſures. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Socrates</hi> warned Men, that they ſhould take of ſuch meates as do prouoke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate when they haue no hunger, and to drinke when they haue no thirſt. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Gorgias,</hi> being demaunded what manner diet of meats he had obſerued that hee had liued ſo long? Hee anſwered, that hee neuer dyd eate any thing for pleaſure or wantonneſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How to blame, and what it is.</head>
               <p>TO blame, is properly of the demonſtratiue kinde, and by accidentes of other kindes, it comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in it all ſortes of euill ſpeaking, as to reproch, to finde fault, to note, to disfame, to carpe &amp; rayle at: Alſo to reprooue, but to reproue doth properly growe of loue: on the contrarie to (to blame) groweth commonly of hatred.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ MANNERS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Countrey is ſpoyled and waſted through the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of euil maners.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The doing of iniurie vnto others, is in twoo fortes, either by deceiptes, or by force: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, of which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> practiſe of the wolfe: the other, of the lyon, and both of them are moſt farre from humanitie. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 2. Epiſt. f. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:9054:20"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Like, as ſome men (by reaſon) of ſome maladie that they haue, and through dulneſſe of their ſenſes, doe not taſte the ſweetenes of meates, ſo thoſe men (that bee wicked, leacherous, couetous, &amp;c.) haue no taſting of true prayſe. <note place="margin">Phillip.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> He ſheweth himſelfe to be a very foole, who for to ouercome the vertues of any one dooth vſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> force of wickedneſſe, for, like as in running, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt get victorie by ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, ſo vertue is ouercome by vertue.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Thoſe thinges, that are euill and filthie, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes filthie, whether they be kepte ſecret, or made manifeſt. <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Euen, as fooliſhnes is oftentimes a diſeaſe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by inheritance, ſo the wicked doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely beget ſuch as be wicked.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Oh good Lorde God, how true is that olde ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (that of a wicked Father) is ſeldome hatched a good Sonne. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Who ſo is deformed of countenance, and of euill manners, he doth naturally bring forth nothing but euill, lyke, as out of one Vipar, ſpringeth another Vipar. <note place="margin">Ecdorus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The Minde.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THat cannot be ſaid a Medecine whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth with an inſtrument of ſteele into a whole and ſound part of the body, but is rather a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cruelty and butcherlike dealing. <note place="margin">Cic pro Seſt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Thoſe that be of a baſe and brutiſh minde, and giuen to pleaſures and luſt, <hi>Plato,</hi> in his firſt booke, <hi>De Republica,</hi> doth banniſh from the holy fellowſhip of Philoſophie, as prophane and vnable to attaine therto.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9054:20"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Like, as a durtie ſoule poole, can not giue foorth cleare water, euen ſo a minde replete with euill thoughts &amp; vile luſtes, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not giue good counſells.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Like as a path (when it is hardened) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hardly be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp &amp; framed to another faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any force, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, a minde lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tyme accuſtomed to ſin, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not by any ſharp and bitter reprehenſion bee corrected and amended.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Slackneſſe in Religion, &amp; an ill conſcience.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> HE that hath once digreſſed out of the waye of trueth, will haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience more to ſweare falſly, then to ſpeake the trueth. <note place="margin">Cic. Pro R. Comedo.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> It is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t only to know God (which thing the very deuils do, that hate hym,) but alſo to make diligent ſearche what God would haue vs to do, which ye may finde in the holy Scriptures, if ye haue the ſprit of God for your Inſtructor.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You ſhall by your ſlacknes in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reape but ſmall fruite in this life, and in the life to come infinit and perpetuall damnation.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I am bonnd to hate the vices of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through their litle religion, and great pertinacie would cary me headlong with them into cuill.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> A wicked man pricked in conſcience, ſuffereth farre greater torments, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any doo by beatings, or by any bodyly afflictions. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> He, that doth diſhoneſt thinges, muſt not looke to haue them kept ſecret: &amp; albeit that he could keep them cloſe from others, yet, they cannot bee hidden from his owne conſcience. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Biantis,</hi> beeyng demaunded what thinge was in this life that was not accompanied with feare?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9054:21"/>A good conſcience, ſayde he.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Periander,</hi> being aſked what manner of thinge libertie was? Anſwered, an vpright conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> What is hee that is leſſe fearefull, &amp; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ſide, more coragious, then the conſcience free from all euill? <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Wee muſt not holde him in admiration that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth in riches, but him whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is quite diſcharged from ſinne, and is made pure. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſmall eſtimation of Frends.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> TO make rehearfall of good turnes done vnto thoſe that haue receiued them, is an vpbray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with the benefite beſtowed, and to note them out, of forgetfulnes and ingratitude. <note place="margin">Terence in Audia.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The benefites that men be checked withall by thoſe that would be accounted benefactours, doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurte, then gratify, and doo ſhewe the ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, they haue of a frende.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> To reproue a man for benefites receiued (is no thing els) but to purchaſe hatred.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> To paſſe a mans life ioyfully with his frends, is a thinge full of conſolation: and on the contrarie, not to vſe conuerſation with them, either for hatred, or for the litle regard that they haue, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perturbation of the minde. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> The troubled minde doth greatly relieue it ſelf in beholding the countenance of the Freends: on the contrarie part, to be voyde of ſuch reliefe, is more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious then a cruell death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Ciuill Warres.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> HEe can not loue dearely the priuat habitations of the citie, the publique lawes, the eſtate of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9054:21"/>libertie, whom diſcordes, homicides, and ciuill war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res do delighte. <note place="margin">Cic. fil. 13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Vnto what other ende doe tende ciuill warres then to make an ende of all good Cittizens, yea, and to bring to confuſion the Cittie it ſelfe?</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> If we call the <hi>Tartarians</hi> and <hi>Scithians</hi> cruell (for they do exerciſe crueltie againſt other Countreys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacent neare vnto them, for to amplifie their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Empire, or for the maintenaunce of their libertie)what ſhal we terme thoſe that for to debaſe and deſtroy their owne Countrey, doo bathe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ciuill bloud?</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Ciuill and inteſtine diſſentions, doo hurte vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally all men (inaſmuch) as they tende as well to the deſtruction of the Vanquiſhers, as of thoſe that are vanquiſhed: Wherefore, loue is good, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concorde neceſſarie to be amongſt perſones. <note place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Crueltie.</head>
                  <p>WHat Tyrant was there euer, who forbad the miſerable to lament? <note place="margin">Cic. pro Seſtio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Who was euer ſo cruell, he forbad me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bewaile within themſelues, and to make ſupplications vnto others? <note place="margin">Contra piſh.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> What Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is there in <hi>Scithia,</hi> which forbad (to them that had occation) to weepe? <note place="margin">Pro R. Amer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Foraſmuch, as nothing can bee ſo holy but that it may bee at ſome tyme violated through preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous boldnes, ther haue ben a ſingular puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deuiled againſt Parricides, to the intent that thoſe that could not by nature bee contained within the limits of good workes, might be withd: awen from the euill and vngratious works through the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the paine.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9054:22"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> What Theeſe is there ſo lewde, or what Pirat ſo cruell, which if hee can obtaine his praye without blood-ſhed, will ſhed blood therfore.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Crueltie is not worthie to be poſſeſſed of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s minde, and hee that will be cruell and vncourteous, muſt of neceſſitie be ſpoiled of humaine and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able nature.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Too much nycenes ingendreth diſpraiſe, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man litle eſteemed, but crueltye breedeth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> It is neceſſarie that a man bee ſeuere in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting lawes: alſo that ſuch a one may bee a patterne (in following himſelfe) what the Lawe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. <note place="margin">Iſeus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Thoſe, that take delight in other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s miſhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, do not know how that the chaunces of fortune be commune to all men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Pride.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> CAn the heartes of wilde beaſtes be tamed, and is the heart of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only implacable? but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart of him is moſt vnappe aceable of all, who hath with crueltie conioyned an incomparable pride.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> This inſolent Perſon, beeing blinded with the ſmoke of his pride, is become inſupportable to hys vaſſailes, odious to others, and to the moſt parte of men more hated then knowen.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Who euer ſawe the nature of any man like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, which hating his ſuperiours, can not abyde his equals, and diſpiſing his Inferiours, ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath no leſſe beaſtlines, then pride in him.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> This man is ſo imperious and proude, that he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9054:22"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding euery man, preſumeth to ſhew fauour to ſome in commaunding.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Socrates,</hi> ſeeinge <hi>Alſcibiades</hi> (who went puffed with pride, and was become very ſtately becauſe of his riches and great landes that he poſſeſſed) ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a large mappe of the worlde, and ſayde vnto him, looke well herein, if thou canſt ſee thy Landes: <hi>Alſcibiades</hi> aunſweared, that hee ſawe them not: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Socrates</hi> replyed, Oh <hi>Alſcibiades,</hi> why art thou ſo lofty minded for thoſe thinges that bee ſo litle worth, that they haue here no place appointed them. <note place="margin">Elianus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Proude men be communely vyle, and through their vylenes and pride they are inſolent in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and in their aduerſitie, they become: abiected &amp; miſerable. <note place="margin">Chilo.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Auarice.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THere is no duetie of frendſhip ſo perfect, nor obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſo requiſite and ſolemne, but Auarice wil hinder both the one, and contaminate the other. <note place="margin">Pro P. Quentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Some were wont for the loue of their Children to bee deſirous of richeſſe, and this man for the loue of richeſſe, hath not cared to loſe his children. <note place="margin">Pro Aulo Cluentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> There is no ſpeedier iuſtice executed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toward a couetous perſon, for, his puniſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ioyned with his ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Socrates,</hi> being reprooued by <hi>Xantippa</hi> his wife, becauſe that hee would not take thoſe many giftes that were brought him, ſayd: If we ſhould take im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly that which is here ready to be giuen, wee ſhould not hereaſter, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we tought therfore, finde any thing to be giuen vs. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9054:23"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> When a certain ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demaunded of <hi>Socrates,</hi> how he might do to become rich, he aunſweared: that hee muſt make poore his luſtes.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> It is good to make election rather of loſſe, then of beaſtly gaine, for that, the one dooth put vs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure but once, the other for euer. <note place="margin">Chilo.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Thoſe that giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a pray, for to get ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, and cannot tel how to eſteeme of them aright when they haue gotten them, be like vnto thoſe that haue a good horſe in the ſtable, and cannot ride. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Diogenes,</hi> likened the couetous men, vnto ſutch as had the dropſie, for how much the more filled, the one is with monie, the other with water, ſo mutch greater is the deſire of the one and thirſt of th'other: to each of which, their greedy deſire is cauſe of their ruine and deſtruction. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> If the deſire of richeſſe bee not bounded within a certaine ſatiety, it is mutch worſe then extreme po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: foraſmuch, as great gredines of hauing bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo great neceſſitie.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> A man beeing very rich, and yet accompanied with a continuall carefulneſſe of hauing more and more, is as like the life of a begger, as of a rich man.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> The richeſſe of couetous men, is like the ſunne when it is gone downe, for it comforteth not, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth cauſe of reioycing to any man.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Auarice, is the greateſt euill that is amongeſt mortall men, for it bringeth to paſſe oftentimes that thoſe which go about to ſerape together, and vnite another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s riches vnto theirs, bee ſo deceiued that they lay and conioyne their richeſſe to thoſe of other men.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9054:23"/>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13 Bion</hi> the <hi>Sophiſt</hi> ſaid, that auarice was the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt mother citie or <hi>Metropolis</hi> of all ribaudrie. <note place="margin">Euſeb.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> Thoſe that liue to heape vp richeſſe together, as if they would ſaue them vntill the other worlde, do forſake (both) themſelues and all their felicitie in the meane ſeaſon. <note place="margin">Antipho.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15 Theocritus</hi> ſayd, there be found many rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which be not Maſters, but Tutors of their richeſſe. <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16</hi> He, that would become rich, muſt not ſeeke to increaſe richeſſe, but to extenuate his affections. <note place="margin">Epicurens.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16 Plato,</hi> ſeeing one wholly giuen to the ſpoile for heaping togither riches, hee reproouing him, ſayde, that he ſhould not ſtudie to increaſe his richeſſe, but to diminiſh his greedy coueting. <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Prodigalitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> HEe hath conſumed vp all that euer hee had, in ſuch ſort that there remaineth at this preſent nothing ſufficient, not onely to ſatiſſie his luſt &amp; deſire, but alſo, for to ſuccour his neceſſitie. <note place="margin">Pro Aulo Cluentio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> A ceriaine prodigall man, wondering at <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes,</hi> becauſe that he had only craued of him ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous almes: I do this (ſayd he) becauſe that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I can but ſeldome get it, of thee neuer. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Crates,</hi> likened riches of the prodigal vnto thoſe figges that firſt come forth, wherewith the crowes and ſuch like fouls are fed, and not men, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods of the prodigal do feede (only) whores, paraſites, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is not ſo much amiſſe to haue riches, as it is to looſe them diſorderly. <note place="margin">Xenophon.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Anger.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 EMNVS,</hi> called anger, the beginning of fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but vnto many it hath beene the ende (both)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9054:24"/>of fooliſhnes, and alſo of life.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> This man is more diſdainfull and angrie, then euer was <hi>Caelius</hi> the Senator, who beeing angrie with one that was his client, the which agreed with him in all thinges, and was obedient to him: yet, hee being full of diſdaine, ſayde, thou doeſt therefore not gainſaye me in any thing, becauſe thou mayſt make vs twaine, twoo.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Although, it is a great matter to vanquiſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, yet, it is a farre greater to know how to foreſee not to ſall therinto. <note place="margin">Dion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Like, as thoſe ſhippes that abyde ſtoutly the raging ſeas, bee accounted more valiant the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others, ſo alſo, men that reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anger &amp; perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the minde, be eſteemed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt conſtant of all others. <note place="margin">Sotion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Euen, as ſmoke troubling the eyes, doth let vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we cannot ſee thoſe things which be afore our feete, ſo wrath aſſaulting the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, dimmeth and blindeth our reaſon. <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Seruaunts, when they are bought, doo not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether their maſters bee ſuperſtitious or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious, but whether they be angrie or not. <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Mancrates,</hi> a wiſe man, ſaid, that angry men bee like vnto lampes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which how much the more they abound with oyle, ſo much the more they flame.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> It cannot be that a man chaufed with anger, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do any thing reaſonably.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Enuy.</head>
                  <p>SOme me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enuying the praiſe of others, doo like the peſtilence infect, and ſpoile our frendſhip.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Enuy doth alwaies extend it ſelf to thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be moſt high. <hi>3</hi> Like, as where ther is no light, is no ſhadowe, ſo where no vertue is, there is no enuy.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9054:24"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Enuy, is onely fed of euill, and is tormented by that which is good, receiuing in it ſelf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euil which it deſireth in others: wherfore <hi>Alexander</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great, ſaid, that enuyous men be their owne tormenters.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is not ynough, that our owne euils, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which be very great, doo torment vs, but alſo other mens bleſſednes, and happy eſtates, do vexe vs.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> There was neuer any famous man, in any age, which dyd not with a haynous countenance wonder at enuy.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Enuy, is one of thoſe Enemies, the which are by no meane better vanquiſhed, then by flight.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Socrates,</hi> being demaunded of <hi>Alſcibiades,</hi> how he might flye Enuy: aunſweared, with liuing an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and miſerable, like <hi>Therſites,</hi> for, that miſerie (alone) is without enuye.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> The enuyous perſon, is an enemie to himſelfe, foraſmuch, as he is alwayes beaten with continual paſſions of the minde. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Ruſt, conſumeth yron: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mothes, cloath: wormes, wood: but enuy, as that (which is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al euils) conſumeth man.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Enuye oftentymes caſteth downe thoſe that haue beene exalted by fortune. <note place="margin">Apollon.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Few men ther be that without enuy doth loue a fortunate Frende.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Theophraſtus</hi> ſayde, that wicked and enuyous men, do not ſo much reioyce of their own benefit, as of another mans hurte. <note place="margin">Sophocles.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Thoſe that are enuyous be the moſt vnhappy of all men, for they do not only ſorow for their owne hurt: but alſo for the proſperitie of others.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9054:25"/>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15 Socrates</hi> was wont to ſay, that enuy is a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the foule. <note place="margin">Democr.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Wanton loue.</head>
                  <p>IF we would conſider howe much exellencie is in the nature of man, and how much worthines, we ſhould alſo ſee how great ſhame it were to ſuffer it to be gouerned by leacherie, by delicate liuing, &amp; by a feminine ſpending of time in voluptuouſnes. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 4. Epiſt. f. 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> It is extreme fooliſhneſſe, to delighte in thoſe thinges, in which is greater pleaſure then profit.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The pricks of louers, the ſlightes that they vſe, the ſnares that they lay, and the deceipts that they ſowe for to poſſede the thing loued, do ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto vs how great the diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of loue is.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Loue, groweth not on a ſodaine, as wrath doth, neither paſſeth it ſodainly away, although it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed to cary winges. <note place="margin">Phitar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Nm. N.</hi> is neceſſarie to gratifie a faint louer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but mutch more him that hath an heart francke of loue. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Loue, can not be ſaid to be any other thing, but a madnes amongeſt men.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Loue, is an ydle thing, vnprofitable for any good enterpriſe, an Enemye to labour, &amp; that it is ſo, we ſee that, it, flying Beggers, ouertaketh rich men.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Loue, is an exceſſe of a certaine vnreaſonable deſire, which commeth quickly, but goeth ſlowly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Theophraſtus,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, what loue was, aunſwered, it is the effect of an ydle Spirit. <note place="margin">Theophraſt.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Surfetting.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IDlenes, is the father of leachery, and gluttonie is the mother.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:9054:25"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Nothing is more vile, or doth more pricke a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then gluttonnie.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Nature hath giuen vs a throate, not for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to delight in ſurfetting, but only for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duite and waye, whereby the meate is guided to the nouriſhment of the body.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Some men ſet all their ſtudie and care vpon knowledge, ſome vppon cheualrie, and other-ſome vpon other honeſt exerciſe: and this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (alone) hath all his minde vpon the kitchin, and in the cookery, (as one who only hath for his ende and purpoſe) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue eating and drinking.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Like, as the roote doth nouriſh the plant, ſo the meate that the bodye receiueth, ought to nouriſhe it ſelf, and not luſtes, &amp; gluttonous eating &amp; drinking. <note place="margin">Muſomius.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Idlenes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> SO great is the ruine and deſtruction of others, that through their imbecillitie, (and not for our owne vertues) we be accompted mightie.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Men beeing in proſperitie and in ydleneſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortune laugheth on them, they become vniuſt, vntemperate, and do ſuffer themſelues to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with voluptuouſnes,</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It is no ſhame to take paines, but ſhame to be ydle.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Vertne walketh by the waye of labour, and not by the waye of ydleneſſe. <note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> It was wont to be ſayd, that exerciſe is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a good name. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> There bee many moe become good through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and good exerciſe, then be by nature.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Goods do multiply with a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he take paines.</p>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9054:26"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Heſiodus,</hi> lykened the ydle perſons to Drones, which be thoſe bees that hauing no ſtinge to defend themſelues, doe eate vp the labours of other bees, without trauailing. <hi>7</hi> A ſound man that is idle is more miſerable, then one that hath the agewe.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Idlenes, cauſeth infirmitie of the body, and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the minde. <note place="margin">Euſebius.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Riches.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> RIches be rather the Friends of vice, then of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and doe oftener allure the mindes of young folke to vnhoneſt delightes then otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Like a horſe cannot bee ruled without a bridle, ſo richeſſe cannot be ordered without prudence.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Euen, as garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which be of themſelues cold, doo not increaſe, but conſerue the naturall heate of man, ſo richeſſe and honours do not make men hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, for as mutch as felicitie conſiſteth in our minde, not in thinges ſubiect to the iudgement of others.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Our nature hath none more deadly enemie then richeſſe, a dire aduerſarie to vertue, &amp; a miniſter of vice: neither did <hi>Diogenes</hi> without occaſion ſay, that vertue dyd not willingly lodge, either within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of a citie, nor yet but in a few rich Pallaces.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Plato,</hi> wiſely ſayde, that a ritch man could but ill willingly be vertuous.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> The intemperate deſires of getting richeſſe bee very prickes and rich thornes. <note place="margin">Antipho.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Richeſſe ill gotten, were wont to breede ſhort pleaſures, and long ſhame. <note place="margin">Epitt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> It is a harde matter for a rich man to bee tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, and for a temperate man, to get great abon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of richeſſe. <note place="margin">Alcides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:9054:26"/>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> It is neceſſarie to haue a rich minde, and not a body clad with a great oſtentation of riches. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> The very fruites of richeſſe, be nothing els but leachery, couetouſnes, and infamie. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Richeſſe bee blinde, and doo make thoſe blinde that behold them.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Garmentes, which bee too long, doo hinder the going, and ſuperfluitie of riches bee an impediment to the ſoule, <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Our affections by nature, are harde to bridle, but after that they be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with riches, they cannot poſſibly be bridled. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14 Bion</hi> ſayde, that thoſe were made a laughing ſtocke which would giue themſelues a praye vnto richeſſe: for they are graunted to a man by fortune, conſerued by Auarice, &amp; gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togither by falſhood. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15 Diogenes,</hi> called richeſſe the vomit of fortune.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16 Plato,</hi> being demaunded what ſtoare of riches a man ought to ſeeke for? anſwered, ſo much as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould breed any ſnares, nor haue neede of any neceſſarie thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Honours.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THis courſe of life which I hold, perhaps I offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in, which do maruail at the brauerie &amp; outward ſhow of this life, and do not diſcerne the carefulnes and great yerkſomnes wherewith it is replete. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 1. Epiſt. fa. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Like, as <hi>Emnus</hi> ſayd, in raigning or gouerning as King, there can bee no true faithfull companion, nor credit giuen to any.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Theſe ſmokes of vaine honour doo ſeeme in my iudgement, to ſerue for nothing els but to make vs ſlaues to the rouling eſtate, &amp; madnes of fortune.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9054:27"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> If we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider diligently, how that theſe honors and worldly dignities, be for the moſt parte vnſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, we ſhall finde alſo that it commeth to paſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they are grounded vppon the inſtabilitie of fortune.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Paſtimes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> FOr to feede the People with the vanitie of ſutch ſhowes, is a thing but litle eſteemed of goodmen, for it noteth riotouſnes, and is nothing worth. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 2. Epiſt. fa. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Like, as it is but ſooliſh wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes to be caried about with a vaine out rye of others, and to follow the ſhadowe of a falſe vertue, ſo it is an act of a wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and vnconſtant minde, to refuſe the light and brightenes of that which bringeth true glorie, and is the moſt honeſt fruite of perfect vertue. <note place="margin">Contra piſo.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not eſteeme good that ſort of pleaſures which hath beene found out by a wicked and naughtie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch a one as hee was: for, nature doth not ſo eaſily admit a naughtie plant to bring foorth good frut.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Wee are ſo by nature enclined to pleaſures and paſtimes, that we delighting indifferently in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and making a confuſion with good and bad to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, do alſo confound our ſelues.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> To what ende do ſerue paſtymes, &amp; gamings? but to ſteale away time, &amp; to buſie our vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vaine thinges, and without any profit.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> All pleaſures ought not to be followed (but thoſe only) which haue their deriuation of honeſt things. <note place="margin">Demoſt.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Beautie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Know not how I m ght praiſe beautie, ſeeing, that in wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is for the moſt part accompanied with cruelty and ingratitude.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9054:27"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> We muſt haue regard to the goodnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, and not to the beautie of the body. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Byon,</hi> confirming the opinion of ſome that ſayd, how that tyranny conſiſted in beautie: ſaide moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyrants a man might by many meanes be deliuered, but from beauty, by no meane. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is a very delectable matter to behold beauty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thinges, (but to touch them) cannot bee without danger: like, as <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſaid, the cooke doth broile only thoſe thinges that hee layeth on the coales: but beautifull things, do ſet on fire alſo thoſe that ſtand neare about them. <note place="margin">Fanorinus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Like, as Gilliflowers and other moſt pleaſant and ſweete ſmelling herbes and flowers, if they bee caſt into a Iakes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt filthie dung, do forthwith become vile, euen ſo beauty, if it be, not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with excellent vertues &amp; graces, waxeth eftſoones, filthie and abhominable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Noblenes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> AL men are in this reſpect equall, that they haue had all one manner of beginning, and were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally created after one faſhion.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> No man can challenge to himſelf any worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for beeing borne of noble blood and of famous parentage, but for that he hath lyued vertuouſly, and dyed valyantly.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The nobilitie of thy parents and blood, do ſerue thee to none other purpoſe, but that thou canſt not keepe thy ſelfe vnknowne when thou wouldeſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> He glorieth of himſelf but in vaine, which boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of his dwelling in a noble Pallaice (inaſmuch) as the praiſe is not his, but his predeceſſours.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9054:28"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> In my iudgement (he that is a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be accounted noble, like, as (on the contrarie part) I eſteeme a wicked man ignoble, although hee were deſcended of a father more noble then <hi>Iupiter.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Nobilitie conſiſteth in prudence: and by vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is obtained true riches, but only at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of God.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> He that by nature is inclyned to vertue, hee is noble, although his mother were an <hi>Ethiopian.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Theodor.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Antigonus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, going about to reproue <hi>Byon</hi> the Philoſopher of ignoblenes, aſked hym what hee was, of what countrey, and where was his Cittie, and his parents? to whome <hi>Bion</hi> aunſweared, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not vnto Freendes to enquire where they were borne: but what manner of men they be. <note place="margin">Bion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> It is better to glorie of the praiſes of the minde then of the nobilitie of the elders, beeing already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed through the obſcuritie of the poſteritie. <note place="margin">Phalarides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Like, as the noblenes of beaſtes dooth conſiſt in the diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſtrength of the body, ſo the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of men conſiſteth in the goodnes of manners. <note place="margin">Democr.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 Diogenes,</hi> being demaunded who were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? anſwered, thoſe which diſpiſe riches, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, pleaſures and life.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Socrates,</hi> beeing aſked of a certaine man, what thing was nobilitie, made aunſweare, that it was a good temperature of the minde, and of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Flatterie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> NO man whileſt that he is in proſperitie can tell whither he be loued or not.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Euen, like as <hi>Acteon</hi> was torne in pieces with his own Dogges, that had beene nouriſhed by him,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9054:28"/>ſo are thoſe torne in pieces by flatterers, that do noo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Flatterers, bee like vnto certaine ſepulchers, in which is only written the bare name of amitie. <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Antiſthenes</hi> ſayd, that there is leſſe hurt founde amongeſt Rauens, then among flatterers, for, theſe do corrupt and eate the mindes of ſutch as bee aliue: the other do but deuour (only) the dead bodyes. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Antiſthenes,</hi> was wont to ſaye, that Flatterers were like vnto curtiſans, or harlots, which do looke to haue found in thoſe that were inamored on them all excellent gifts, except Iudgement and wiſdome. <note place="margin">Pathagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Crates,</hi> ſeeing a yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who was very weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, accompanied with a multitude of Flatterers, he turned vnto him and ſayd: Oh young man (I am ſory) to ſee thee ſo ſolitarie.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Demetrius Phalerius,</hi> exhorted <hi>Ptolome</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, that he ſhould buy him bookes to read, ſutch as trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of well gouerning a Kingdome: for, in them hee ſhould finde written ſuch things, as thoſe that were his true Freendes, durſt not, and his falfe Freendes would not ſhew him. <note place="margin">Iſeus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Ingratitude.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IT was a generall fault of all them which did not defend me, and (eſpeciallie) of ſuch as were bound thereby by duetie. <note place="margin">Dio. 1. Epiſt. f. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> All the good that I haue done for him, is as good as loſt, for, it is euen like, as I had done the ſame to mine Enemie.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It was wiſely ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were two woundes in good turnes: the one reprouing or vpbrayding of benefites beſtowed: the other, forgetfulnes of ſutch,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9054:29"/>as haue beene receiued, both of them be the mothers of vngratefulnes, and ſtepmothers to a good turne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Malice.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THeir maliciouſnes, maketh them to credit that which they haue hath ſay of others: that is, that I muſt debaſe my ſelfe. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I ſhould neuer haue beleeued that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſo litle haue eſteemed our recyprocall loue, &amp; the freendſhip renewed amongſt vs, that for one onely worde, thou wouldeſt ſeeke to deſtroye my Brother <hi>Metellus,</hi> neither reſpecting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noblenes of our houſe, nor yet the great loue that I haue borne vnto you and to the common wealth, the which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations might haue moued you, to haue put vp a litle iniury. <note place="margin">Cic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The iniurie which that naughtie toungued fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hath offered to this good yong man, hath made his moſt ſhamefull and impudent life manifeſt for euer. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <note>¶ Vide Cic. Pro Rof. Amer.</note>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> ME thinketh that how much the more mightie and noble a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, ſo much the leſſe he ought to ſhewe foorth his power, eſpecially toward the ruine of poore men. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Go not you about with honeſt wordes of your letters to cloake the diſhoneſtie of your minde, for thoſe that haue already an yll opinion of you, will giue no credit therto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Doltiſhnes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> OH God, what a cockeſconbe is he: and how in amoured on him ſelfe without any modeſtie or reaſon. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Hee is ſo ſenceleſſe and doltiſh, that nature ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9054:29"/>euen to haue brought hym into the Worlde for deſpite.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> There be found ſome ſorte of men in the world ſuch ydiotes in their talke, that looke how more they go about to beautifie &amp; inlarge their talke, ſo much more they are mocked rather then harkened vnto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Compoſing or applying of thinges amiſſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> MEn haue vſed many times to adorne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with glorious words found out by other mens induſtrie. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Thoſe men that in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pyling or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſing works (do nothing els but imitate others) are in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like vnto the popingaye or pye, which ſpeake thoſe thinges that they do not vnderſtand.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Like, as he cannot runne wel, that ſeeketh to ſet his feete onely in traces of another mans feete, ſo thoſe cannot write well which go on imitating, and neuer ſwarue from the boundes of others. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ This life.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Wiſt not that this life was ſhorte, &amp; a vaine courſe of glorie. <note place="margin">Pro Seſtio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Of good, and of euill, conſequently of godly men and of vngodly, there is at this preſent no great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count made: ſuch is the life wherin we do liue.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Our life (when fortune doth fauour) is like to a running brooke, which is all durtie and myrie, harde to get into, viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, making a great roaring &amp; noyſe, and laſteth but a while. <note place="margin">Epitt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> This our mortall and miſerable life is none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the likenes of a ſhadow, and a birth vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the earth. <note place="margin">Sophocles.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:9054:30"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> The Sea and land is full of euills and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which daye and night doo compaſſe about this troubleſome life. <note place="margin">Heſiod.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Good things (although they be ſought) doo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come, but on the contrarie (euils things) doo come on heapes without ſeeking. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Man, is none other thing but an example of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, a ſpoyle of time, a ieſt of fortune, an image of inconſtancie, and a ballance of enuy &amp; calamitie: remaining (only) fleagme and choler. <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> This (our life walking through a circle) is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſubiect to bee intrapped with euill, and can neuer abyde in one eſtate. <note place="margin">Herodotus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> This our life (trauailing alwayes toward the ende) is like vnto wine, whereof (a litle being left in the bottom of the barrell) doth become vineger. <note place="margin">Antipho.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To be ſory.</head>
               <p>TO lament, or to be ſorowfull with another, is an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that groweth of the diſpleaſure &amp; griefe that we receiue by our owne misfortune, or by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune or hurt of that perſon with whome wee do lament or ſorrowe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For the death of ſombody.</head>
                  <p>THe death of your father (a man of moſt worthy memorie) hath depriued me of a teſtimonie of gret authoritie, vnto whom I was moſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 2. Epiſt. fa. 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Albeit, that I am aſſured that I can not bring you more hurtful newes then theſe, yet, becauſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or rather the prouidence of God is ſuperiour to all men, I haue thought good (not to holde my peace herein) howſoeuer the matter goeth.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:9054:30"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> In this reſpect the nobleſt and moſt valiant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the worlde, is no better then equall with the ſimpleſt and him that is moſt vile of conditions, for, that with one bitter ſorte of death, the liues of them (both) are extinguiſhed alike. <note place="margin">Cic. 4. Epi. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Sithens, that it hath pleaſed God (who is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deceiued) thus to deale, it is expedient that wee be conformable to his will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For ſickneſſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> WHo doth not ſee, how that many times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hurt which we receiue by the Phiſitian, is worſe then the malady it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Concerning ſickneſſe, ſome ſorte of them were wont to come through efficient cauſes, as by exceſſe of heat, or of drought: ſome by materiall cauſes (that is) by want of nooriture or ſurfetting: otherſome are bred in certaine, the naturall partes of man, as in the blood, in the marrowe, or in the braine: at ſome other times, ſicknes alſo do proceed of exteriour cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: as by the water (being vnholeſome, by the ſoyle of the countrey, by ſurfetting, by penury, and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) by which meanes, I ſuppoſe that your ſicknes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, wherof, for the loue (that I beare you) I am very ſory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For pouertie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> MY griefs doo not only flowe through the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of yours, but they doo alſo increaſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly. <note place="margin">Cic. 9. ad Att. Epiſt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The Goddeſſe of pouertie, as beeing moſt hatefull, is without any Temple. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Pouertie, is no ſmal maladie to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proue it. <note place="margin">Diphilus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> There is no chaunce more miſerable in this our life, then pouertie: for a good &amp; vertuous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9054:31"/>he be poore) is nothing eſteemed. <note place="margin">Crato.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Man hath no greater enemie then pouertie.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> A poore man, as one that is fearefull, is euen a ſemblance of feare it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Men doe communely account of ritch men that they be wiſe, and on the contrarie make but a ſcoffe at poore folke, although they be godly &amp; vertuous.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For impriſonment.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> It is ſo cruell a wound that I beare in my Spirit for this your impriſonment, that I aſſure you, I of vſe no better eaſement nor reſt in my minde, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hape that I haue to ſee you recouer againe your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtate of libertie.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I doo ſo greatly lament, for this your impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is conuenient for our fréendſhip, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, like as I (at this time) I am exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieued, ſo (I hope) that hereafter my conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall be the greater, when as I ſhall ſee you reſtored again to your former libertie, and honorable, eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Exile.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 OH wretch that I am, that I ſhould be the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ſo manyfolde troubles, and ſo mutch the more wretched am I, as that your valiancie, your goodneſſe, and gentleneſſe, deſerued better fortune then this. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib 14. Epiſt. fa. r. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Seeing, that no conſolation can be greater then this that I deſire rather then my life: namely, that I might dye in thine armes, for as mutch, as by no meanes I can ſo hope of thy deliuerance, &amp; that thou mighteſt be rewarded, according to thy deſerts.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Ariſtides,</hi> being demaunded, wherefore he tooke ſorrowfully his ſending into Exile? he aunſwered,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9054:31"/>becauſe of the ſhame that my Countrey receiueth of the iniurie done vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For libertie loſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Neuer deſired at any tyme my fortune more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, then to haue the accompliſhment of the thing I now deſire in theſe your tribulations, to let you vnderſtande howe that I eſteeme your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie loſt, a yoke of ſeruitude vppon my necke: and albeit, that the reſidue of your Frendes be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame minde, yet, I haue thought good to make manyfeſt vnto you mine affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ye may meaſure it with your own affection, and with the affection of others, and haue experience therof.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> What greater miſfortune can happen to noble mindes, then the loſſe of libertie yet (I truſt) you wil play the parte of a wiſe and valiant man, diſpoſing your ſelf, according to the quality of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I ſhould lament for your libertie loſt much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I doe, but that I perceiue how that fortune ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſclaues of ſuch, as by vertue were made free.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Reputation loſt.</head>
                  <p>It is very lamentable that other mens wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe haue defiled the brightnes of your name.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If thou ſhalt ſhewe a valiant minde in theſe thy miſhappes: I can neuer praiſe thee vnto the full, but much ſorrowing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for thine eſtate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Who wil ſay, that he is ſpoiled of his orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who by death is exalted to euerlaſting honours.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> The chaunge of fortune is grieuous ynough to one that was ſometimes happy &amp; fortunate: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he that hath alwaies bene in aduerſe fortune, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9054:32"/>not ſo mutch ſorowe at the familiaritie of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Calamities haue dominion ouer men, and not men ouer calamities. <note place="margin">Herodotus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To comforte or giue conſolation:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>And (firſt) for olde age.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knowe no cauſe why me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that olde age is ſubiect to ſo many maladies, ſeeing, it is euen infirmitie it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That old man is more fooliſh (who hauing paſſed ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daungers of this life, and is arriued at the ende of them) would wiſh to begin his courſe newe again, then a trauailour, who hauing ended a longe and yerkeſome iourney, ſhould deſire to go it ouer againe immediatly (foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much) as nothing is more acceptable to ſuch as bee weary, then reſt and lodging.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It is not expedient for your wiſedome, to wiſh for that, that ye haue loſt, ſeeing, it cannot be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, that is youth, for it is the propertie of a mad man to loue that which is loſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Men ought to reioyce whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come vnto age, wherefore they were borne, ſeeing age, is the very rypenes of men, and is as profitable to be in men as in fruites.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Death.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> DEath happeneth to al men alike, wherfore thou oughteſt not to challenge vnto thy ſelfe a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of life aboue others.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I dare not take in hande to comforte thee, or to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9054:32"/>offer thee any ſuccour, for, I knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou art wiſe ynough, &amp; of a moſt noble minde, wherfore it ſhould ſeeme great preſumption if I would go about to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter thee conſolation in this matter. <note place="margin">Cic. 5. Epiſt. 17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> All things that be according to nature, be good: and what is more agreeyng to nature, then for an old man to dye.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Thou oughteſt to conforme thy ſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of God, and to beleeue that hee knoweth better what we need then our ſelues, and the time when to drawe again to him ſelf his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> In the raging Sea of this oure tempeſtuous life, we haue none other hauen, ſaue death.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Thou mayſt thus comfort thy ſelfe for the loſſe of thy Father, that ſithens in his life tyme hee liued well, he hath now with death obtained rewarde of his vertues.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> This world is a very Uallaye of waylinges, deepe, obſcure, and full of mire: happy is he that wel getteth out of it.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Seeing, it is ſo ordained by nature, that he which firſt cometh, muſt firſt go: the ſonne hath no cauſe to lament for the death of his Father, for, hee dooth not therby forſake him, but goeth before him.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> We may (truely) call the Earth a better Mother vnto vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe that hath borne vs, for, ſhee nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs but for a fewe monethes: and the other for a great many yeares.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> To lament for things that can not be gotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, groweth rather of too mutch fooliſhnes, then of much godlynes and loue.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9054:33"/>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Uertue, may make honeſt any ſorte of death, whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Albeit, that my minde is not ſufficient to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, for that the ſorrow that I abide doth ſuffer me to haue no place of conſolation, yet, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> He was not borne in vaine that dyeth well, neither liued he vnprofitably that finiſhed well his life.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Death is no death, but the end of trauailes, and a beginning of life.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> There is no armour more ſtrong againſt any cruell dart of fortune, then a prudent minde: and I, being of opinion that you are moſt wiſe, do beleeue alſo that you vnderſtande, howe that no humaine thing can bee perpetuall or quiet.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15</hi> If thou wouldeſt conſider, howe that hee was borne a mortall man, thou wouldeſt not ſorrowe of his death.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16 Socrates,</hi> beeying demaunded, what was the greateſt beatitude of man? Hee aunſweared, to dye well. <note place="margin">Eſchines.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17</hi> If ſicke men could be healed with teares, and that forrowe could ceaſe their griefe, I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende this wayling. <note place="margin">Philomenes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <hi>18</hi> Inaſmuch as we be mortal what thing ſhould we els looke for of this our life, but mortalitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For Health loſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Truſt with the grace of God ſhortly to ſee thee not only free from this diſeaſe, but alſo from all ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, by meanes of this ſicknes, wherby thei ſhal be conſumed, veryfiyng the olde Prouerbe (that is) that one euill dryueth away another.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9054:33"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Nothing (new or vnwonted) is happened vnto you, neither hath fortune any iot changed cuſtome, nor nature, beeing alwayes vnſtedfaſt, vnconſtant and blinde, but we may rather ſay, that in this your maladie, it hath vſed the owne proper and naturall conſtancie, which is, to be alwayes vnconſtant, and neuer to abyde in one eſtate.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Sicknes is a great dehorter from vices, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and an exhorter to modeſtie and goodneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is mutch more eaſie to abyde the infirmitie of the body, then the griefe of the minde, wherefore, I thinke it good that in this your ſicknes, yee ſhake of all ſuch thoughts as might trouble you.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Although, that man by nature is accompanied with many euills, yet, the worſt of them all, is the diſpleaſure of the minde, take heede therfore, leaſt ye ſet any thing raſhly to heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of reputation loſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Am glad that your fortune is vnlike mine: for ther is great difference betwixt beeing iniuried, &amp; bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng vtterly vndone. <note place="margin">Cic. 1. Epiſt fa. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> To be without doubt is toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a good hart, which thing without all peraduenture, would both ſtaye, his fooliſh rage, and bringe you againe to your due place of honour. <note place="margin">Cic 1. Fa 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The courſe of your fortune, although the caſe be vnlike, yet it ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth to the ſame end that mine doth. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> To the grieuouſnes of the ſorrow that I feele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your matters, I haue yet this conſolation, that I truſt the counſels of Frendes, and the time it ſelfe, which breaketh the appointments of wicked men, ſhall giue recompence to the wicked willes of your enemies. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:9054:34"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Concerning this loſſe, if you ſhal make ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as I haue alwaies denied that you ought for to make, you ſhall doe wiſely, and ſhall with victory triumphe ouer your Enemies. <note place="margin">Cic 3. Epiſt. 20.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> The refuge of our ſtudies is ſuch, that although wee cannot haue the great loſſe wee had reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wee may yet at the leaſt bee ſomewhat eaſed by not thinking theron. <note place="margin">Lib 4. Epiſt. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Doeſt thou not remember how that with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall lamenting, thy troubles bee rather doubled, then raced out of memorie.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Canſt not thou ſee things that are open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, who with thy quickneſſe of wit waſt wont to pearce to the knowledge of thinges moſt ſecret? Canſt not thou know how that continuall lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng doth relieue thee neuer a whit. <note place="margin">Lib. 6. Epi. 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> A man, that is rightly vertuous, ought to looſe nothing by the multitude of the wicked: <note place="margin">Lib. 9 Epi. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Thy valiancie is ſo great and worthy of it ſelf, that for the ſuſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, thou needeſt no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of others, neither can I well comfort another, which am depriued of all conſolation, my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Like, as in the aboundaunce of good fortune we are not ſtraight loſt, ſo, wee ought not to diſpaire in the anguiſh, wherinto this fearfull waue hath tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported vs. <note place="margin">Lib. 7. Epi 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Albeit, the diſtaining that is vſed to thy honor, is not to the loſſe of my health, yet, there is ſuch like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes betwixt them, that me thinketh we could not be ſure Frendes, except we taſted both of like greefes. <note place="margin">Lib 1. Epi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Mans eſtate, was wont thus oftentymes to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, neither is there any thing ſtable vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9054:34"/>he which yeſterday was a Seruauant, to day is become as a King: and another, who of late went clad in fine Purple, and commaunded the people, is now clad in vile ragges, and become a bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſeruant.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14 Pittacus</hi> ſayde, that it was the duety of a wyſe man to know how to ſkirmiſh with aduerſitie, and the part of a valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beare the ſame modeſtly. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Goodes loſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> LIke, a wyſe and valiant man, thou needeſt not care if the vnhoneſtie of men ſhall robbe thee of thoſe things, wherewith fortune hath indewed thee moſt bountifully. <note place="margin">Cic. 1. Epiſt. fa. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I confeſſe that thy griefe is ſuch, as thou canſt hardly receiue any conſolation, ſo great is the loſſe of all thy ſubſtaunce, and ſo litle hope of recouering the ſame againe: but yet, thou oughteſt to moderat thy ſorrowe, and not vtterly to diſpaire. <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Epiſt. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Nobodye is more vnhappy in my iudgement, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he, whome fortune hath not earſt ſuffered to taſt of her venim: for, like as the ſhadow accompanieth the ſonne, ſo aduerſitie followeth glorie &amp; renowne.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> The long experience that I haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in you, concerning wordly thinges, eaſeth mee of taking in hand to adminiſter you any conſolation (inaſmuch) as I knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you were wont to arme your minde againſt the darted of fortune, I doo therefore veryly beleeue that yee will patiently abyde this burthen of pouertie, that without any fault of yours, is falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vppon you.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Truely, your loſſe of richeſſe is great, but I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme that you ſhall make it mutch greater, if you ſhall alſo looſe your ſelfe.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:9054:35"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Wee muſt not beleeue that fortune loueth thoſe men more, vppon whome it fawneth, and ſuch as it neuer diſpleaſeth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe whom it exerciſeth with continuall trauailes: for, like as proſperitie maketh men fortunat, ſo doth aduerſitie make them famous and tryed.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Whileſt that you torment your ſelf for the loſſe of richeſſe, that you haue ſuſtained, you do (without doubt) make the ſame greater: for, ſorrowing for the loſſe of richeſſe, you debaſe the worthineſſe of your mind, which teacheth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deſpiſe worldly things.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> The loſſe that ye haue ſuſtained, is not ſo great but that your wiſedome is greater: wherfore with Iudgement correct fortune. <hi>9</hi> It is better a godly poore man, than a wicked ritch man, for, the one is worthie of mercie, the other of reproofe. <note place="margin">Antiph.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of the loſſe of Friendes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IT is now time to put in practiſe the precepts that haue beene written by moſt wiſe men, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thy ſelfe to the vſe of ſuch things as with long ſtudie thou haſt learned: which thing (if thou wilt) thou mayſt (though not willingly, yet at leaſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently) abide the want of thoſe Frends whom thou haſt loſt. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 7. Epiſt. fa. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> He, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of terrene goods, as of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp;c. knoweth how prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and with modeſtie to beare fortune, he may be truely called happie.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Verely the loſſe of ſo deare a Frend, which you haue ſuſtained, myght ſhake the ſtouteſt heart that is: but (foraſmuch) as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with any chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that happeneth in this world, it is your part to be greatly comforted in conſideration of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9054:35"/>honeſte and faithfull freendſhyppe maintayned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> You ſhew your ſelf not to be thoroughly taught in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip, ſithens you ſorrow at the death of ſutch a freende, who liued ſo well, that there is no doubt, but the Angels haue caried him into the ſight of GOD, to enioye the fruites of his vertuous la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> It is the parte of a wiſe man not to bee ſory for things loſt, nor glad for ſuch as be preſent. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Wee ought not to bee ſorye for the death of our deare Friendes, ſeeing, they muſt of neceſſitie dye: but rather for ſuch as dye beaſtly. <note place="margin">Pollien.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Impriſonment.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> LIke, as a man that is ſound and in good health, hath no neede of a Phiſitian: ſo a wiſe man hath no neede of conſolation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Doo ye not vnderſtande, that he alone may bee called a worthie and valiant man, who neuer bowed his ſhoulders at the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of miſfortunes, who neuer blamed nor panted at his chaunce: and inaſmuch as it is ſo, you ought alſo in this impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhewe the libertie of your minde, altogether couered with armour of your innocencie.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It is leſſe hurt to be impriſoned vnworthely, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue vndeſerued libertie, and to ſuffer wrong in defence of iuſtice, then through lewdnes to abound in wealth.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> What thing els is the earth, but a litle Ilande, compaſſed rounde about with the <hi>Ocean-ſea,</hi> in the which we are put, as in a priſon.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> You haue great cauſe to comforte your ſelfe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9054:36"/>in this trouble, and to giue God tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes that he hath ſo endued you with his benefites, that like, as in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie yee dyd not want wiſedome, ſo your courage and valiantneſſe of minde hath not fainted in this impriſonment.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> If it bee true that the eſtate of vertuous &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men doth conſiſt in the force of the minde, &amp; not in this corporall matter: I repute any parte of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation at my handes towardes you, to bee but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, whoſe noble heart I know, is at libertie, in this your vndeſerued impriſonment.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> The priſon doth not miniſter ſo mutch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the wicked, as it dooth glorie vnto the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whoſe vertue doth afterwarde ſhine more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently then afore, like a fire that hath beene kepte ſecret and after bruſeth forth in great flames.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> If you had by any meanes deſerued thys im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, there were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe why I ſhould ſeek to comfort: but ſithens that the malice of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is the only cauſe therof, I leaue giuing of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to your ſincere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of a moſt verteous life, truſting to ſee you here after much more exalted then you are nowe diſgraded.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Socrates,</hi> being demaunded, howe a man might liue without troubles? hee denying that to be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſayde: A cittie or an howſe cannot bee without thoſe that dwell therin, and frequent the ſame. <note place="margin">Antiph.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Thoſe, that with waylings and lighings doo take in yll parte their miſfortunes are vnwiſe, and do not remember how that many be, and haue ben in a like and in a worſer eſtate. <note place="margin">Hipparcus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 Appollodorus,</hi> ſorrowing and lamenting for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9054:36"/>
                     <hi>Socrates,</hi> becauſe he was vniuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned to die, <hi>Socrates</hi> laughing ſayd to him thou therfore (which art my deareſt Frend) wouldeſt haue me iuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned. <note place="margin">Xenophon.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Exile.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THat death is not miſerable that is receyued for the common weale, neither is that Exile lothſome that is cauſed for vertue. <note place="margin">Cic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Epiſt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If they ſhall take my life away, yet they ſhall not bereaue me of my reputation, though they ſhall afflict my body with Exile, for that, it is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: yet, they ſhall not remooue my minde from the common wealth.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Defend thy ſelf ſtoutly from ſorrow, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande Fortune, reuoluyng alwayes in thy minde howe that in our Cittie, and in the common weale many haue vniuſtly beene ſent into exile: I tell thee alſo (and I would to GOD, it were not true) that thou art dryuen out of ſutch a Countrey, where no good wiſe man can liue quiet.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I do not only exhort thee, but doo alſo pray thée for the frendſhips ſake that hath beens betwixt vs, that thou wouldeſt ſtabliſh thy minde againſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, conſidering with thy ſelfe in what eſtate all men are borne.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Your moſt noble minde, hath no need of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon medecine, and that which I ſhould ſaye for to comfort you in this your exile ſhould be as a ſhadow in reſpect of the light of your vnderſtanding.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Hee, which is vniuſtly ſent into exile, ought to make himſelfe mery, for that he hath Iuſtice his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of his exile, which ſuffereth the vngodly Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizines to perſecute him.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9054:37"/>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> The heart of a valiant man, dooth not faint at the firſt falling of fortune, and what els is this your exite, but a diſfauour of one chaunce of fortune for a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terpaiſe of infinit fauours, that ye haue receiued of her.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Great folly it is to lament the dying out of ones Country, foraſmuch, as it is ſuperfluous to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to the place where a man ſhall ſtaye, dying, when as he muſt immediatly depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all places.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Anaxagoras,</hi> dyeing out of his countrie, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by his Frendes, whether hee would haue his body caried to the place where hee was borne? He aunſwered, that the waye that leadeth to Hell, is no further from one place then from another.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Like, as the Mariners haue inſtruments pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared (both) for proſperous and for aduerſe ſailings, ſo ought we to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affections of our minds made fit (both) for good and ill fortune.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> In what place foeuer a man be, hee hath one &amp; the ſelfe ſame waye continuall and plaine to walke thorough this frayle and mortall life, to an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and euerlaſting life. <note place="margin">Titus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Ydle fellowes, and ſuch as are good to nothing, are belieged with pouertie, euen in their countryes: wheras, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie part, ſuch as be induſtrious and wife, in what part of the world ſoeuer they bee, do poſſeede ſufficient, and neuer feele want.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Euen, as going out of one ſhip into another, we may ſtill ſayle proſperouſly, ſo going out of one Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or countrey into another, wee may leade our life fortunately.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14</hi> Like, as euery qualitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire is penetrable
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:9054:37"/>to the eyes of the Egle, ſo euery Cittie and countrie is to a valiant man.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15</hi> In what part ſoeuer it be of the world, where the earth doth nooriſh vs, there is our Countrey. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16</hi> Seeing, that we are by nature brought foorth all free and vnbou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I know not by what reaſon we ſhould afterward binde and reſtraine our ſelues to one corner.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17</hi> Euery part of the World, is free and open to a wiſe man, and to a valiant minde, the whole world is his Countrey. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Pouertie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THou waſt wont to comforte others, following the maner of ignoraunt Phiſiciants, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king profeſſion to haue ſkill in other folkes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, know not how to cure their owne. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib 4. Epiſt. fa 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I beleeue that in theſe corrupt and tempeſtuous times there is any thing that can drawe neere to the true beatitude, ſaue only. ioyfull pouertie.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Poore men, that do content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with their eſtate, be deare vnto God. <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Diogenes</hi> hearing, the pouertie of a wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprooued, fayd: I neuer ſaw any tormented for hys pouertie, but for wickedneſſe. <note place="margin">Elianus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Diogenes</hi> ſaid, that pouertie was a learned ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour to Philiſophie: forſomuch, as thoſe things that Philoſophy forced to perſwade with words, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame were put in practiſe by pouertie.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> If thou ſhall neuer deſire much, a litle will ſeeme to thee ynough. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Drogenes,</hi> made this a anſwe be to one that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed pouertie to him for a fault, oh vnhappy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9054:38"/>I neuer ſame any man become a Tyrant thorough pouertie, but many thorough richeſſe.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> The life of poore men, is like vnto a ſayling at Sea, when the ſhip is neare to ſhore, but the life of ritch men, like to thoſe that ſayle in the depth of the Sea: To the one ſort, it is eaſie to caſt auker, and to fall into harborough: To the other, it is more hard, and requireth great labour. <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Like, as it is better to lye ſounde and in good health vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſimple matteriſſe, then beeyng ſicke to lye vppon a large and rich bed: ſo alſo it is better to liue fortunately in meane fortune, then vnhappyly in great aboundaunce. <note place="margin">Epitt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Pouertie, is not that which cauſeth vs to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but the ouermuch greedyneſſe of our mindes.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Many men for iniuſtice and euill doyng haue beene put to death, but for pduertie neuer any.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> No man is more fortunat, then a poore man, for, hee neuer feareth to fall from an highe eſtate to a lowe. <note place="margin">Diphiſus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13</hi> Pouertie, is a thinge that is not enuyed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth any man ſtriue to obtaine it, and without any garding it is defended and conſerued: And how much the more, it is deſpyſed, ſo much the more it is exalted. <note place="margin">Xenophon.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:9054:38"/>
               <head>¶ To bewaile or lament:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>And (firſt) for death.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had no comfort leſt me, but only this, wherof death hath depryued me. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 4. Epiſt. fa. 6. Ad Attic. Lib. 1 Epi. 8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> What great ſorrow and griefe I haue ſuſtained by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of what commoditie (both) publike and domeſticall, I haue beene thereby depriued of, you (who knowe my ſecretes) may conſider, for, looke what conſolation one man could enioy by another, al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I receiued at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The death of <hi>Lentulus</hi> (beare it as we can) is ſuch, that we haue loſt a very good and worthie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who had the noblenes of hys minde tempered with an infinite humanitie.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I know not what thing can bee acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a man, that hath loſt him, who was wont to bee more deare vnto him, then any other thing.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> The death of this Noble man hath ſo pearced into my Spirit, that I can neither finde words, nor reaſons, that be able to comfort my ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For things done vnto vs.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am wel pleaſed at this that thou haſt tried what credit is in men with thy ſmall coſt, as well as I knowe to my great dammage. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 1. Epiſt. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> We were caught in a ſnare, or at the leaſt ſore belayed and like to haue beene caught.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I beare theſe thinges with a faire face, and a mery countenaunce, but in very deede, they doo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly deſtroy and conſume me. <note place="margin">Ad Attic. Lib. 5. Epi 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Thou ſeeſt howe thinges doo fall out, for there is no manner of euyll in the worlde, that I doo not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9054:39"/>at this preſent abyde, and doe looke for to abyde hereafter.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> It is a notable ſayeing amongſt men, that it is but a ſmall matter to reprooue one, but to abyde an iniurie receiued, is a burthen inſupportable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of tymes.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> ALL the laudable cuſtomes of our councry bée now decayed and vtterly come to nothing. <note place="margin">Cic. 3. Epi. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Our Countrey is afflicted and oppreſſed thorough the miſerie of the time.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The malice of theſe tymes is ſo great, that no remedie is able to diſcouer and make manifeſt the minde from thoſe ſorrowes that ſhadowe it.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Roome,</hi> is at this time giuen to the ſpoyle, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice hath there no place: to conclude, all good lawes and cuſtomes be there reiected. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I doubt not, but that thou knoweſt how that at this preſent, the worlde is full of deceiptes, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blinges and lyes.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Graunt vs ſome reſpit to writ of dolefull and miſerable matters, conformable to theſe times. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Wheras in times paſt, wee had great fauour, great authoritie, and moſt great renowne, nowe all theſe thinges be quite gone. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> I ſpend all my time in reading, not for to finde any medicine which might heale mee, but for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſorrowe that doth now oppreſſe me.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Who is ſo diſſolute, that he can at theſe thinges hold his peace and keepe ſilence.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Wee can ſee in theſe miſerable dayes nothing but trouble, and anguiſh to hang ouer our heads.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> The le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of time, cauſe vs to ſee many things,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:9054:39"/>and to abyde much that we would not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Fortune.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THY Letters had bred in me a great ſorrowe, but that I haue euen determyned with my ſelf to make a ieſt at Fortune. <note place="margin">Cic Lib 2. Epiſt. fa. 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> My heart is ſo hardened with continuall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire that I can admit no newe ſorrowe into it.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The penſifenes of my heart hath ſo tormented and ſpoyled me, that I am euen at deathes dore.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Oh enuyous fortune, howe readye art thou to chaunge the very ſame benefites, that thy ſelfe haſt giuen vs?</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> When will this winde of euyll fortune ceaſe? neuer: The which tranſporteth mee from flood to flood in the Sea of worldly aduerſitie, and wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuffer me to ſee, or take ground.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Fortune, is ſometimes our mother, ſometimes our Stepmother in one and the ſame day. <note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Fortune doth not giue, but lendeth monie to rich men.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> There is no hauen of richeſſe ſo ſtrong, but it may be broken by occaſion of yll Fortune. <note place="margin">Bion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> I haue often tymes ſeene nobilitie vanquiſhed thorough Fortune, and thoſe that haue beene nobly borne, haue vnworthely ben caſt downe by fortune. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To demaund:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>and (firſt) of Ayde.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N recompence of thoſe honours that thou haſt receiued by my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, thou oughteſt to bee contented, that I may leane ſomwhat vppon the ſupport, &amp; with thy luſty flowriſhing youth to be ſome ayde vnto my feeble old age. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 1. Epiſt. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:9054:40"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Thou knoweſt how greatly thou mighteſt help me now, neither do I require ought els at thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but that which thou ſhalt iudge to bee for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment. <note place="margin">Lib. 3 Epi. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> In this reſpect you may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d greatly my freend, if that like as you promiſed me, ye will at al aſſayes be the Protectour of me and mine, whenſoeuer need ſhall require. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> If you will proceede on to bee ſuch a patrone &amp; Defendour of men as ye haue beene: <hi>Publius</hi> and <hi>Vatinius</hi> will alſo ſeeke for your frendſhip &amp; ayde. <note place="margin">Epiſt. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I would y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye would place this matter of mine, in the Regiſter of your owne affaires, to th'ende that I may with you here obtain thoſe things that you haue put in my head to labour for. <note place="margin">Ad Attic. Lib. 11. Epiſt. 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip that in this matter yee might vſe towardes me, is ſo great that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be expreſſed, in which my neceſſitie if you would (as eaſily yee may, ſtand my good Friend and Patrone) you ſhall both ſhew the excellencie of your valiant and true noble heart, to your no ſmall honour, and alſo ſhall binde me as an humble &amp; obedient Seruaunt with all manner duetyfulnes towardes you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Fauour or grace.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> ESteeme thus with your ſelf, that if ye will in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſhewe me courteſie, you can in no wiſe better fauour me then in this gouerning of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. 1. Epiſt. fa. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I wilbe contented with any thing that ye ſhall do for me, but if you will acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh thys my requeſt, ye ſhall be the better ſatiſſied.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Albeit, I haue ſufficiently tryed howe great-your
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:9054:40"/>loue is towarde me: yet without doubt I ſhall be the better reſolued thereof if I may obtaine this preſent fauour at your handes. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. Epiſt. fa. 21. Lib. 9.14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> For the ſtrict bonde of frendſhip and loues ſake that is ioyntly betwixt vs, I requeſt thee of grace, that thou wilt vouchſafe to vſe ſuch curteſie and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie toward the <hi>Volteranes,</hi> as, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Lib. 10. Epi. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I, being an vndoubted teſtimonie of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thot I beare vnto you, &amp; hauing already ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced the loue that you beare vnto mee, haue been bould to requeſt ſo much gracious fauour at your handes.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Notwithſtanding, that I doo not doubt, but yee wil vſe the ſame liberialitie towards vs, which you haue for your ſakes heretofore imployed (inaſmuch) as ye are not vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: yet, we would craue at your hands that ſinguler grace which you firſt promiſed, and earſt vſed, to bee nowe extended towardes vs aboundantly. <note place="margin">Lih. 13. Epiſt. 25.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Seeing, that I am altogether out of hope of euer deſeruing your loue by merits of ſeruice, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greatnes of your fortune &amp; the ſimplenes of mine, I will indeuour my ſelfe hence foorth to meryt ſome grace at your handes, by crauing and by ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inaſmuch, as yee may of your vertuous diſpoſition as well eſteeme, the indeuour of an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble well wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heart, as of ſuch as do you diligent ſeruice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Counſell.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THou ſhalt bee hee, who in all matters of mine ſhal be my counſellour, &amp; ſhalt take the charge of mine honour, lyke as thou haſt done of my health, and I will be at all times ready to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thy will &amp; decrees. <note place="margin">Cic Lib. 1. Epiſt. fa. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:9054:41"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I doo not ſo mutch requeſt your counſell for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch in my buſineſſe, as to obtaine honour in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with others, knowing, that to bee, wiſe and prudent, will be profitable both to him that counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and to the Counſellour.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I eſteeme more, to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayled at your hands, then I do to be aided by a great multitude of others together, for, on their ayde dependeth nothing but a litle profit and honour, which (I knowe) is much regarded of you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Pardon.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Do humbly therfore with all reuerence and duty that I can, deſire pardon.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had not falne in this lewdnes or offence, for the which I craue pardon of your grace, neither had my<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fortune be diſcouered, nor your clemencie &amp; nobleneſſe of heart beene made knowne &amp; famous, as by this meane it ſhall.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I requeſt pardon for ſuch a thing as ſhalbe well worthie your grace to graunt me.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I knowe not, in what matter I euer offended your worthines: but ſithens that ye be offended, I humbly aſke pardon, promiſing neuer to giue you any cauſe of offence againe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To Exhort:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>and (firſt) to the feare of God.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raying, and ſuch godly exerciſes be eaſie to ſuch as ſeeke the way to ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I admoniſh you that yee deſtroye our ſpirituall Enemies, which be vices, &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall luſtes, and that ye giue the ſcepter and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of your ſpirit and inwarde partes to the feare of God.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:9054:41"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I exhort you as earneſtly as I can to the feare of God, whereby you may looke for an, aſſured and perpetual beautitude, if ye wil firſt cut off all vaine deſires that be fruitleſſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi>There be three vertues vnto which euery man ought chiefly to applie himſelfe: the firſt is to honor and feare of God: the next dutie is, to the Parents that haue begotten vs and brought vs vp: the third duetie is to the Prince and Lawes: which who ſo obſerueth ſhall acquire to himſelf a moſt beautifull crowne of glorious fame. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To liue well.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IT is now time that we leaue ſetting our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s on this miſerable and moſt ſhort life, and ſeeke for that life which is happy and perpetuall. <note place="margin">Ad Attic. Lib. 10. Epiſt. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Beleeue me, the only waye of praiſe dignitie &amp; honour, is to be praiſed and beloued of good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of ſuch as be wiſe. <note place="margin">Pro P. Seſtio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I exhort you as earneſtly as I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye would begin a new habyt of liuing, and vſe ſuch manners as tende vnto vertue, which may make the minde more capable of felicitie.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Conſider with your ſelfe how that the beautie of the minde is ſo much more greater, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the body, as a thing that is endued with diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, being famous &amp; euerlaſting, is more wortthie then that thing that is obſcure, terrene, &amp; frayle.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Foraſmuch, as humaine prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is but a dreame in reſpect of a well gouerned Spirit, let vs vſe the counſaile and diſcretion, that God hath appointed.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I do you too wit, that to liue well &amp; vertuouſly, is a thing that will better ſatiſſie euery bodye, then any thing els.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:9054:42"/>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi>When as at a certaine time one ſayd to <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> that mans life was ſull of afflictions and euils, not the life, ſayde hee: but the yll liuing. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi>A wiſe man, when hee goeth on a long iourney, doth prouide (rather) for thinges neceſſarie, then for ſuch things as be precious and coſtly. <note place="margin">Plato.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Like, as an houſe or a ſhip muſt haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lower partes very ſtrong, ſo the beginninges and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our actions, ought to be true and iuſt. <note place="margin">Demoſt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Spenſippus,</hi> beyng willed by <hi>Diogenes</hi> to leaue that ſitting ſtill in a corner that hee vſed, &amp; to ſtretch out his legges with going, anſwered: that hee liued not by legges, but by vnderſtanding. <note place="margin">Fanorinus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Vnto vertue.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> YE muſt haue an eye to that which <hi>Plato</hi> did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely write, that ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were wont to be cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, as were the moſt excellen and worthie men in a Cittie. <note place="margin">Cic. Lib 1. Epiſt. fa.9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Thou muſt wholly indeuour thy ſelf to ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues as may get thee eternall fame, if thou wouldeſt attaine to that degree that thou deſireſt. <note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Epi 4.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Thou muſt of neceſſitie anſwere to that expect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the People haue conceiued of thee, if thou wilt looke for any preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which thing thou maiſt eaſily accompliſh, if thou ſhalt applye thy ſelfe to a vertuous life.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> We eſteeme that the bodies of worthie and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant men bee only immortall, and that the motions of the minde and vertue, deſerue perpetuall glorie. <note place="margin">Lib. 3 Epi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Let vs loue our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, let vs obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Senate, let vs imitate the godly: let vs diſpiſe the benefites of this preſent life, and let vs ſeeke for vertue, accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be moſt good, which ſhalbe perfectly iuſt.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:9054:42"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Him do I deeme an able and worthie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who aſcendeth to an hygh degree by hys owne vertues, and not him that aſcendeth by another mans fall &amp; miſerie. <hi>7</hi> Couet to get thee frendſhip, not with al thoſe that ſeeke to be ſrends with thee, but with ſuch as ſhall be worthy men, and ſuch with whome thou mayſt well gouerne the Cittie. <note place="margin">Pro Roſcio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> It is conuenient that men doo holde in greater pryce the ſowle then the body: for, the ſoule is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt perfect ſubſtaunce of man, and the body is but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of the man, euer chaunging and vnperfect. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Like, as an huge image muſt bee ſet vpon ſome foundation, ſo ought a man be founded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honeſty without euer ſhaking or being remooued.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Ageſilaus,</hi> King of <hi>Lacedemonia,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what were the thinges that appertaineth to a Prince? hee anſwered: bold courage againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, good will toward his Subiects, and readynes in giuing good counſell. <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 Zeno</hi> ſayde, that the moſt precious ornaments of a Cittie, were the vertues of the Cittizens. <note place="margin">Eſchines.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Like, as a lanterne ſet on the toppe of an high cliffe, nouriſhing with a litle oyle a great flambe, is a ſuccour to Mariners, that paſſe that way thorow the deepth of the Seas, euen ſo is one good Cittizen a great helpe to many others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To the obedience of the Prince.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Admoniſh you for your owne quiet and wealthes ſake, that ye ſhew obedience vnto hym, whome it hath pleaſed GOD to appoint a Prince euer you, wherof ye ſhal neuer faile if that you ſhal but mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his great power and dignitie with your owne ſimple eſtate.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:9054:43"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> It is an ancient ordinance of lawes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiectes ſhould yeeld reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and obedience to their Prince. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Epaminundas,</hi> ſeeing a goodly great hoaſt of men without a gouernour, ſayd: lo, what a multitude of beaſtes are here without any head. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Solon,</hi> being demaunded, howe a Cittie might be brought vnto a perfect eſtate, aunſwered, when as the Cittizens ſhall obeye the magiſtrate, and the magiſtrate the lawes.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Foraſmuch, as Princes are vpon earth, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and lieutenants of GOD himſelf, who, but meere <hi>Atheiſtes</hi> ſhall dare preſume to rebel againſt, or not to obeye their ſoueraine Prince.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To the obedience of Elders.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IF you will follow the way that your Elders haue taught you, ye ſhalbe in good hope to come to gret preferment and dignitie.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Thoſe haue attsined to a great parte of vertue and rightuouſneſſe, which do reuerence ſuch as bee worthie of reuerence. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The hands of young men bee ſtrong to labour, and the opinions of old men, be apt for counſell. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is an olde ſaying, that the worke of younge men, and the counſell of old men, haue great force.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To the obedience of Parents.</head>
                  <p>HE, that reuerenceth Father and Mother, is, not only in his life, but alſo at his death, acceptable to God. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Hee, that feareth and willingly obeyeth his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, is like (without doubt) to become a good citizen. <note place="margin">Orpheus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> God hath reſpect vnto ſuch as withal reuerence do giue preheminence to their Parents.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:9054:43"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Behaue thy ſelfe towarde thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen like as thou wouldeſt haue thy Children do vnto thee. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Pittacus,</hi> reproouing a mans Sonne that would contend with his Father, vſed theſe wordes, if thou ſhalt ſpeake any thing amiſſe vnto thy father, thou ſhalt be blamed therfore, &amp; if there ſhall be nothing amiſſe, yet, thou ſhalt be deemed worthie blame. <note place="margin">Elianus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> A certaine young man comming from ſtudie, whereas hee had heard <hi>Zeno</hi> many yeeres, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by his Father, what thing he had learned in ſo long ſpace? he aunſwered, that he would ſhew him: but foraſmuch, as hee ſhewed it not forthwith, his fatherin a cholor fell vpon him, &amp; did beate him, which beating, he ſupporting patiently, ſaid: I haue learned with patience to beare my Fathers anger.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> If thou be vngratefull toward thy Father and Mother, nobody will iudge thee to bee euer mindfull of any benefite, that they haue done vnto thee. <note place="margin">Xenophon.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To fauour the common weale.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THere is nothing that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breed thee greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and glorie, nor of all worldly thinges that can bee more famous and worthie, then too doo good to thy Countrey. <note place="margin">Cic. 10. Epiſt. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I would exhort thee to goe forwarde with that honorable enterpriſe that thou haſt in hand: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that of thy ſelfe thou haſt already done more for the common weale, then I could demaund, I ought rather to reioyce with thee therefore, then to exhort ſhee. <note place="margin">Ad Attic. Epi. 7. Lib. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> That is a true Glorie, and an vndoubted praiſe of vertuous actes, and of excellent deſertes toward
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9054:44"/>the common weale, the which is approoued not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the teſtimonie of all good men, but alſo by the common ſort and all. <note place="margin">Cic Fil.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is our duetie to prouide for theſe things, and for this cauſe bee wee placed in this eſtate, that as out of an high windowe, we might diſcry counſaile a farre of, and with our wiſedome to make the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale without daunger and feare.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> It is the duetie of ſuch as we are, to abide with a watchful minde, alwaies to do, to thinke, or to ſay, ſomwhat for the common weale.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> He, that luſtely defendeth his Countrey, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for death, enuy, or puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in reſpect therof, ſuch a one may (truely) be called a man. <note place="margin">Fro Milone.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Pithagoras</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, in what ſort a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may deale againſt an vngratefull Countrey? aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared: as againſt his owne mother. <note place="margin">Euſeb.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To Conſtancie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THere remaineth nothing els for me to doo, but to praye &amp; exhort thee, that thou wouldeſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thy minde againſt all aduerſities of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and that thou wilt remember (not onely thoſe things that thou haſt learned of worthie men) but alſo thoſe vertues that with good nature and ſtudie thou haſt atchieued. <note place="margin">Cle. 4. Epiſt. 13</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Wee haue ſeene (aforetyme) howe that ye dealt wiſely in the proſperity of fortune, and that ye wan great praiſe therby: Let vs now ſee alſo how well you can behaue your ſelfe in aduerſitie, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any great care therfore, ſo as your noble heart may not ſeeme debaſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Deale ſo as your gentle diſpoſition and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9054:44"/>learning may help you to paſſe away valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the iniurie that ye haue receiued. <note place="margin">Lib. 6. Epiſt. 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I would haue you to bee of an heart (not onely quiet) but alſo valiant and ſtrong, <note place="margin">Pro Milone.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Be of good courage, ſo that if the malicious wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſeeke to diminiſh your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, trueth may make knowen their malice, and your worthines: and that whereas they ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to quench the ſame, they may kindle more and more, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flames of your vertue. <hi>6</hi> Beate down vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoke of your worthiues this calamity, tread it down with the feete of your wiſdome: for there is no tree that hath ſo firme &amp; ſure rooting, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hath beene beaten with many bluſtering blaſtes of winde. <hi>7</hi> He, that hath a ſure and ſtedfaſt minde, doth eaſily obtaine a perfect &amp; ſtedie end of all thoſe things that he deſireth: but he whoſe mind is feeble and wauering, is neuer ſafe from the hurtes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, in what place ſo euer he be.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> There can no miſhappe chaunce vnto him that groundeth hys foundation vpon wiſedome, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and continencie.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Thou muſt ſtraine thy ſelfe to beare the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of fortune with a valiant minde.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Like, as the good ordering of the body maketh vs eaſily to ſupport (both) cold and heate, ſo the good diſpoſition of the minde, maketh vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant to beare anger, diſpleaſure, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of humaine affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> If thou wilt be a Lord as well of thy ſelfe as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer others, deale ſo, as thou mayſt rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande thine appetites, then thy vaſſailes. <note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Sophocles,</hi> ſhewing to <hi>Pericles</hi> a very beautyfull
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:9054:45"/>young man, hee anſwearing, ſayd: it behooueth (Oh <hi>Sophocles</hi>) him that beareth rule, to haue not onely contynent handes, but alſo contynent eyes. <note place="margin">Ariſtippus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To patience.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> IF any thing happen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to our expectation or worthines, let vs be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with patience to abide it, euer looking for better, when God ſhall ſee time.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> We ought with patience to abyde thoſe things that ſhall happen, which humaine wiſedome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remeady, alwayes comforting our ſelues with thinking, that nothing is happened vnto vs, more then hath happened to others aforetime. <note place="margin">Cie. 5. Epi 20,</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I will neuer leaue exhorting you to that patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is proper to a wiſe man, as yee are, and that yee perſwade yourſelfe to bee ordered, according to the will of God, who foreſeeth all thinges.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Looke, howe much the more cruell the Maiſter is, ſo much more famous becommeth the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſeruaunt.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> If you ſhall with greater patience abide to bee vanquiſhed, then ſhall you bee Vanquiſhours, yee ſhall be alſo reputed more valiant then they.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I wiſh you to apply your ſelfe, according to the qualitie of the time, abyding patiently your preſent aduerſitie, againſt which ye cannot preuaile.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> I exhort you that yee vſe the Armour of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and patience: for, with them ye ſhall vanquiſh the force of enuy.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Foraſmuch, as the chaunces of thinges are not applyed to our willes, it is expedient that we apply our will to thoſe chaunces. <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Our life is like to dice-playing, wheras me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be contented with their chaunce. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:9054:45"/>
                  <head>¶ To gratefulneſſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> OVght not we to ymitate the fertile feelds, which do yeeld much more fruit then they receiued.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> If yee remember what I haue done for you, yee will not forget to recompence the ſame againe, as duety bindeth you to doo. <note place="margin">Cie. ad Q. &amp; C. Rom.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It is the part of a gratefull People to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thoſe Cittizens that haue been friendly to the common weale.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I will neuer ceaſe to do well vnto the common weale, &amp; if it ſhall bee gratefull towards me, I will be glad thereof, and though it ſhall be vngratefull, in ſuch a weight matter, I will in ſimplenes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience do it good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To louing kindneſſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> VAliant Knights do raigne and beare aucthoritie more actiuely with a milde and pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Reyne or bridle, then with an harde and diſpleaſaunt.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Aboue all things I exhort you that ye continue ſtill your olde louing kindneſſe towardes euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for, as it is an olde prouerbe, the fauour of euery ſimple body, auaileth ſomwhat.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Like, as garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doo couer the naked preuities of the body, ſo doth louing kindnes and gentleneſſe couer the defectes of the minde. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Ariſtotle,</hi> being reprooued for that he had giuen almes to a wicked man, which begged it of him, hee aunſweared, I giue not this to the lewde fellowe, but to humanitie. <note place="margin">Solon.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Scipio,</hi> willing to keepe the memoriall of <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> laboured not to returne home to his houſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night, except he had firſt gotten ſome Friend and familiar companion.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:9054:46"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> If thou would go about to adorne a Citie with any manner race orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: firſt of all, thou oughteſt to beſtoare thy ſelf with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſingular orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which bringeth with it, humanitie, iuſtice, and liberalitie.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> A Prince, or he that is in authority, ought rather to deſire that his vaſſayles ſhould reuerence, then ſeare him. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To the good education of Children.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> COnſider with your ſelfe how that ye ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue no greater richeſſe, nor worthier dignitie, then good education.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> You ſhall liue after your death, in the life of your Children, if yee ſhall bring them vp in ſuch ſort as they may chooſe the good, and forſake the euill. <note place="margin">Photion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Learne to bring vp thy Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo as they may (not only feede the body) but alſo thy ſpirit with food of immortalitie. <note place="margin">Plato.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> It is our part to ſeeke for perpetuitie of our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and to leaue behinde vs ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to God. <note place="margin">Dion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> To beget Children, is a thing naturalll, but to bring them vp well, proceedeth of a Godly loue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To flye ſlouth.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> ALL the diſcourſes and motions of our minde, ought to bee exercyſed, either in giuing honeſt cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes, which appertaine to good liuing, or els in ſtudying for knowledge and ſcience.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> All hurtes whileſt they bee newe and freſh are eaſily healed, but if thou ſuffereſt them once to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and waxe old, they take ſuch roote as hardly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be euer rooted out or cured. <note place="margin">Phillippica.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> There is no thing amongſt men ſo high &amp; diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9054:46"/>which, mans wit can not attaine, but without trauaile and paines, none can ariue at the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch things as may make him better &amp; worthier, then the ignoraunt and doltiſh ſort of people.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Labour and trauaile, is adioyned with vertue and renowne, and he that flieth the one of theſe, ſhal neuer attaine to the other.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Foraſmuch, as no thing is worſe then ydlenes, I wiſh you, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue ſpace &amp; time, you will do ſo much as write ſome newes to your Friendes, and eſpeciallie to me, who loue you moſt dearely.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I exhort you, to flye ydlenes, and to ſpende your time in the beſt and moſt honeſt exercyſe that ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for nothing doth more hurt time, then time it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> No worthie thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be accompliſhed without paynes taking, and God doth willingly helpe ſutch as be deligent. <note place="margin">Sophocles. Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Labour, is no labour while it is a dooing: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, it cauſeth ioy.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Zeno</hi> ſayd, that man had no greater neede of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, then of time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ To Studie.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> I Would that thou wouldeſt let paſſe all ſorrowes and vaine paſſions, and wouldeſt addict thy mind to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudy of doctrine, the which in proſperity would bee an ornament vnto thee, and in aduerſitie would ſuccour thee. <note place="margin">Cic. 5. Epi. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I praye thee hartely, that thou will followe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, as thou haſt begonne too do, for that doth nooriſh vs with a moſt pleaſaunt hope.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> It is a thing worthie praiſe, and gratefull to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery body that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould trauail in thoſe ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which may profit many. <note place="margin">Pro L. Murena.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:9054:47"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> All other things be to no purpoſe in mans life, but the vſe of good ſtudies maketh a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delightfull in his youth, beloued in his age: is to vs an orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in proſperitie, a refuge and comfort in aduerſitie: it is a pleaſure to vs when we be at home, and no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedyment when we be abroade: it abydeth with vs alwayes, in bedde, in our iourney, and in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, wherſoeuer we be.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Seeing, mans wit is mutch like to yron, which being occupied, doth looke bright, and lying ſtil, both ruſt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume: let vs then ſpend our ſelues rather in famous ſtudies, then in obſcure ydlenes.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Demoſthenes,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, by what meanes he had obtained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art of an Oratour? he anſwered: by ſpending more oyle then wine. <note place="margin">Dethocri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Like, as in battaile the force of yron or ſteele is more worth then of gold, ſo is ſcience in this our life more of value, then richeſſe. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To parle or deſcant:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>and (firſt) of pleaſaunt Speeches.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Bathes are become very whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, contrarie to their cuſtome, but peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, they be inamored with thee, and doe apply themſelues to thy neceſſitie, forſaking their own nature for to ayde and help thee, which thing if it be true, I will not greatly meruaile it Heauen and Earth doe leaue their naturall proprietie for to do thee ſeruice. <note place="margin">Cic. 4. Lib. 8. Epiſt. 13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I am fully reſolued to come vnto thee, and for to ſee and viſyt thee, and alſo to ſuppe with thee, for, I thinke that though thou haſt the gowte in thy feete,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:9054:47"/>yet thy Cooke hath it not in his handes. <note place="margin">Cic. 9. Epi. 25.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Diogenes,</hi> being demaunded of a certaine man, why he went not to abyde amongſt the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which might praiſe him? he aunſwered, that albeit the Phiſitians applied them ſelues to ſeeke the health of men by medicines, yet they did not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to ſuch as were in good health. <note place="margin">Dion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Democritus,</hi> ſeeing one theefe lead to the priſon by aleuen men: Oh villaine (quoth he) that haſt rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſo litle, &amp; not rather waſt able to ſteale ſo much as might haue cauſed all theſe men that lead thee to be caryed alſo to priſon. <note place="margin">Serimus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> When, as a certaine theefe would haue excuſed himſelfe to <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> ſaying, that hee knewe not that he had ſtolne any thing of his: Yea (quoth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi>) but it was ynough that thou kneweſt it to bee thine owne.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Diogenes,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, wherof it came that men beſtowed almes rather vppon ſutch as were halte and lame, then to Philoſophers, becauſe (ſayd he) they feare that they ſhall ſooner become halt and lame, then Philoſophers. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Graue Sentences.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> ME thinkes that a Captaine cannot guide well an Armie, except he firſt gouerne wel himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> The commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, except they be kept in ſome awe and good order, do nothing well.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> One hurt neuer commeth without another.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Ieſting, and merry talke muſt bee vſed, like as men do vſe ſalt in their meat, that is, ſparingly. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Whileſt that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do flye death, they ouertake it.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Diogenes,</hi> was wont to ſay that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do prouide
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:9054:48"/>many things neceſſary for their liuing, and but few thinges that appertaine to liue well. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Ariſtides,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, what thing it was to be iuſt? anſwered: not to deſire any thing, that is another mans.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Demades</hi> ſayd, that the ſhamefaſtnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of a woman, is the rocke of her beautie.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to ſeeke meanes for to hyde his wickednes with wordes, but to amende them with reproofes. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Thoſe thinges that are diſhoneſt to bee done, are much more diſhoneſt to be ſpoken.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> Arrogant Perſons, are like to armour that is gilded without, for their inward parts, do not agree with the outwarde.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Age and mariage, are much alike, for we wiſh for them both, and when they are come, we be ſoone weary of them. <note place="margin">Theod.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Seleucus,</hi> the Lawgiuer to the <hi>Locrenſes,</hi> ſayd, that the lawes were like to ſpyders webbes which catch ſmall flyes, but the waſpes and bees, flye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough them. <note place="margin">Plato.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Subtill and wittie Sentences.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 SOlon,</hi> being demaunded, why he had appointed no puniſhment for ſuch as ſhould kill their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? becauſe (ſayde he) I thought there would be none ſo wicked to commit ſuch a part. <note place="margin">Pro Roſcio. Amer.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 Ariſtotle</hi> ſayde, that thoſe which went about to ſhewe forth things that were manifeſt already, did like as if they would ſhew the light of the ſun with a candle. <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Eſope,</hi> vſed to ſay, that euery bodye caried with
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:9054:48"/>him one purſe or ſachel before, and another behind: in that behinde he did put hys owne faults, in them afore other mens faults. <note place="margin">Euripides.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Pitha,</hi> the Daughther of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> being demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what was the beſt coulour of all others? aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that which did growe in the ſhamefaſtneſſe of wittie countenaunces. <note place="margin">Democri.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Like, as wyne filleth emptie bottels, ſo doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion with fooles.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Theanus,</hi> beeing aſked, what was the duetie of a matrone? he aunſwered, to pleaſe her Huſband. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> A certaine <hi>Romain,</hi> being reprooued of his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, becauſe, he had forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wife, which was honeſt, rich, and beautiful, he holding out his legge, ſhewed his foote, ſaying, here is alſo a new &amp; well faſhioned ſhoe, and yet ye wil not beleeue how it greeueth me. <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Nobody can gouerne a Horſe well without a bridle, nor riches without reaſon. <note place="margin">Plato.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Socrates,</hi> beeyng demaunded, what manner of men handy craftmen were: ſuch (ſayd he) as deſpiſe their equals. <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Diogenes,</hi> ſeeing one who earſt had beene very rich, and through prodigalitie was come to extreme penurie, ſupping with hard fare, ſaid, if thou haddeſt afore time eaten on this faſhion, thou mighteſt haue ſupped better now. <note place="margin">Pithagoras.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To giue thankes:</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>and (firſt) for goodwill ſhewed.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Make greater accounpt of this good diſpoſition of your mind towards me, then of any other thing that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looke for at your handes. <note place="margin">Cic. 4. Epiſt fa, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> It is a confort to me for to knowe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:9054:49"/>that you beare me the like affection that euery man beareth vnto himſelfe. <note place="margin">Lib. 16. Epi. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> I ſee the great loue, which <hi>Caeſar</hi> beareth mee, wherof I more eſteeme, then of all the dignities that I can euer receiue by him. <note place="margin">Ad Q. frat.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I feele great delight in the good will that <hi>Caeſar</hi> beareth me, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I do for all the promiſſes that he hath made me: for, I am not ſo greedy of honours and renowne, as I am deſirous to haue his goodwil continued towardes me. <note place="margin">Lib 2. Epiſt. 18</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I receiued your Letters, which were very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnto me, aſwell for the newes contained ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as for your goodwil therby expreſſed: and I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke you moſt hartly (both) for your certyfying me of the one, and of the other.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I aſſure my ſelfe vndoubtedly of the loue that you beare mee, the which I meaſure by the recypro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call loue that I alſo beare you.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> My man hath made relation to me of your ſo great goodwill which you beare me, and of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care that you haue of me, that although you had neuer done mee pleaſure earſt in all my life, yet, for this cauſe I would hold my ſelfe continually bound vnto you.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> I thanke your lordſhippe (moſt humbly) for the good report that you made of mee, for which (your great curteſie and noble goodwil, though otherwiſe) I cannot by any ſeruice be able to deſerue the ſame, yet I will not ceaſe to render vnto your honor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall thankes, and dayly to praye for you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For benefites receiued.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Remaine your Debteur, &amp; ſhall alwayes thinke my ſelfe bounde vnto you, for the benefit you haue
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:9054:49"/>beſtowed on me, who am Inferiour to none of your Frendes. <note place="margin">Cic. 4 Epiſt. 11</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> As often, as I looke vppon my wife, my children, my houſe, or my Countrey, ſo often doo I ſee the great benefites and good turnes, that you haue done me.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> You may immagine eaſily with your ſelfe how laudable a thinge it is to doo good for others, in as much as I eſteeme my ſelf greatly renowned by the benefites that I receiued at your handes.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Our Lord God graunted me children, and you haue reſtored them to me againe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy were loſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> I will honor the memorie of your good turne done vnto me with an euerlaſting beneuolence, not only while I liue, but alſo, ſo as your fame may abyde after my death.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> If I ſhould do nothing but ſpend all the reſidue of my life. in ſhewing my ſelfe gratefull to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors of my welfare, it were but my duety, ſithens I can make them no amends.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Foraſmuch, as the baſenes of my poore fortune is ſo ſimple, and the worthines of your merites, and benefites towardes me, is ſo great (I truſt) that you will vouchſafe (wheras no other recompence can be had) to content your ſelfe only with the gratefulnes of my heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For fauour receiued.</head>
                  <p>YOur lordſhip (who had neuer fayled to ſtand my Freend) haue now euen drawen mee out of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and ſet me in good eſtimation, whereof, I will neuer be vnmindfull nor ſhew my ſelfe vngratefull whileſt I liue.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I giue you infinit thankes for the freendſhippe which at my inſtance you ſhewed to my Friend, the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:9054:50"/>which thing was as acceptable vnto me for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that I had to ſatiſfie his neede, as that, I take it for an euident argument of your infailable goodwill that you beare me.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Your moſt louing letter was intermingled with ſo many, and ſuch great demonſtration of your loue towardes me, as I might therby haue cauſe to yeeld you aboundance of thankes as to my eſpeciall fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> I am to giue you thankes (not only for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour that you haue ſhewed me) but alſo, I abyde in your debt, &amp; that vnder ſutch a condition, that though not fully (yet to the vttermoſt of my power) I will at ſometime requite your curteſie.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Although your fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip ſhewed me in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not by me be recompenſed with the like, yet, I will neuer forget my duty towardes you for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For commendations receiued.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> THat fame, which groweth by any man of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and aucthoritie, doth greatly encreaſe the reputation and credit of him that is prayſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> I cannot tell, in what ſort I might recompence your curteſie, except, it be in labouring to veryfie in ſome reſpects, the report, that you haue made of me.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Seeing, that you for the loue that you beare me haue giuen me ſuch commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as better might haue beſeemed mee to haue giuen you, I ſhall abide your Debter therfore.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> The praiſes that you haue vttered of me, albeit that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heare of them without being aſhamed, yet, I thus account, that in as mutch as you can not flatter, you haue made this report of meere goodwill that you beare me, wherfore I giue you moſt hartie thankes.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:9054:50"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Concerning the commendations that you gaue me, whither you think as you ſay, or that you faine like a Poet, I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke you hartly for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at a learned mans hande, yea though (it were faſly) cannot be without credit.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> The praiſes that you vnworthely attributed to my wrytings do aſſure me that you haue a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of me, and that the moſt part of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil eſteeme greatly of that which you allowe.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> I doo ſo greatly eſteeme of the prayſes that you geue mee (by which I ſee that I am in your fauour) that it maketh me to thinke ſometimes the better of my ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ For being aduertiſed.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 I</hi> Giue you moſt hartie thankes, for that you haue vouchſaued to write vnto me what was your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and iudgement herein.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> Euery point of your letters were ſo farre from offending me that I account them moſt louing and deare, and for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I giue you moſt humble thankes.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> The Letters ſent by your lordſhip, doo declare how much my duety encreaſeth towardes you, day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Your letters pequire no other aunſwere at my handes (ſauing) that after the good hope and frendly aduertiſementes (wherewith you ſtill incyte mee) I may haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more &amp; more to giue you thankes, and ſo mutch the more thankes, as that the fruit of your deligence and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, dooth more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abounde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="pithy_sayings">
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:51"/>
            <head>Certaine worthie ſentences, very <hi>meete to be written about a Bed-chamber, or to</hi> be ſet vp in any conuenient place in a houſe.</head>
            <p>
               <label>1</label> THe good Son, grafteth goodnes, wherof, ſaluation is the fruit, But the euill pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth vices, the fruit wherof, is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>2</label> Therfore, at night call vnto minde,</l>
               <l>how thou the daye haſt ſpent:</l>
               <l>Praiſe God, if naught amiſſe thou finde:</l>
               <l>If ought, betimes, repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>3</label> Thy bed is like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue ſo cold,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſleepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuts thine eyes,</l>
               <l>Reſembleth death, the clothes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mowlde</l>
               <l>in graue when as thy body dryes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>4</label> Therfore, let not thy ſluggiſh ſleepe,</l>
               <l>cloſe vp thine waking eye:</l>
               <l>Till with aduice and iudgement deepe,</l>
               <l>thy dayly deedes thou trye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>5</label> Who any ſinne in conſcience keepes,</l>
               <l>when he to quiet goes</l>
               <l>More venterous is, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſleepes,</l>
               <l>with twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty mortal foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>A briefe Table, for the readier <hi>helpe to finde out, euery particuler matter,</hi> contained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The manner or Methode, howe to reioyce, what reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is, and of the particuler cauſes wherof (moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) men doe reioyce. Vidz.
<list>
                     <item>OF Health. Fol. 1</item>
                     <item>Of health recouered. Fol. 2</item>
                     <item>Of dignitie obtained. Fol. 3</item>
                     <item>Of dignitie promiſed. Fol. 4</item>
                     <item>Of Gooddes gotten. Fol. 5</item>
                     <item>Of Inheritance gotten. Fol. 6</item>
                     <item>Of frendſhip gotten. Fol. 7</item>
                     <item>Of a Reconciliation. Fol. 7</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9054:51"/>
                     <item>Of being in a good Opinion. Fol. 8</item>
                     <item>Of returne from a Voyage. Fol. 9</item>
                     <item>Of returne out of Exile. Fol. 10</item>
                     <item>Of Letters receiued. Fol. 11</item>
                     <item>Of Matrimonie. Fol. 12</item>
                     <item>Of Childbirth. Fol. 12</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ Howe to wiſh or praye for. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>TO praye for health. Fol. 13</item>
                     <item>To praye for Dignitie. Fol. 14</item>
                     <item>For proſperitie. Fol. 15</item>
                     <item>For a benefit or a good turne. Fol. 19</item>
                     <item>For Libertie. Fol. 17</item>
                     <item>For Peace. Fol. 17</item>
                     <item>Not to be in an euill opinion. Fol. 18</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to aduertiſe, what it is, and wherin to aduertiſe. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>TO aduertiſe one to worke warely. Fol. 19</item>
                     <item>To beware of Errours. Fol. 20</item>
                     <item>Of trayterous dealings. Fol. 21</item>
                     <item>Of Enemitie. Fol. 22</item>
                     <item>Not to fall in an euill opinion. Fol. 25</item>
                     <item>Not to ſpeake amiſſe. Fol. 26</item>
                     <item>To become circumſpect in writing. Fol. 27</item>
                     <item>To knowe himſelfe. Fol. 29</item>
                     <item>To adminiſter Iuſtice. Fol. 30</item>
                     <item>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue &amp; maintain health. Fol. 34</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to blame, what it is, and for what cauſes. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>TO blame euill maners. Fol. 32</item>
                     <item>To blame an euill minde. Fol. 33</item>
                     <item>To blame ſlacknes in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and an euill conſcience. Fol. 34</item>
                     <item>The ſmall eſtimation of Frends. Fol. 35</item>
                     <item>Ciuill Warres. Fol. 35</item>
                     <item>Crueltie. Fol. 36</item>
                     <item>Pride. Fol. 37</item>
                     <item>Auarice. Fol. 38</item>
                     <item>Prodigalitie. Fol. 40</item>
                     <item>Anger. Fol. 40</item>
                     <item>Enuy. Fol. 41</item>
                     <item>Wanton loue. Fol. 43</item>
                     <item>Surfetting. Fol. 43</item>
                     <item>Idlenes. Fol. 44</item>
                     <item>Richneſſe. Fol. 45</item>
                     <item>Honours. Fol. 46</item>
                     <item>Paſtimes. Fol. 47</item>
                     <item>Beautie. Fol. 47</item>
                     <item>Noblenes. Fol. 48</item>
                     <item>Flatterie. Fol. 49</item>
                     <item>Ingratitude. Fol. 50</item>
                     <item>Malice. Fol. 51</item>
                     <item>Doltiſhnes. Fol. 51</item>
                     <item>Surpoſing or applying thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. Fol. 52</item>
                     <item>To blame this life. Fol. 52</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ Howe to lament, or bee ſory, what it is, and for what occaſions. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>FOr the death of ſome body. Fol. 53</item>
                     <item>For ſickneſſe. Fol. 54</item>
                     <item>For pouertie. Fol. 54</item>
                     <item>For Impriſonment. For Exile. Fol. 55</item>
                     <item>For libertie loſt. Fol. 56</item>
                     <item>For reputation loſt. Fol. 56</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:9054:52"/>
               <item>¶ To comfort or giue couſolation, in ſundry reſpectes. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>AGainſt old age. Fol. 57</item>
                     <item>Againſt death. Fol. 57</item>
                     <item>For health loſt. Fol. 59</item>
                     <item>Of reputation loſt. Fol. 60</item>
                     <item>Of Goods loſt. Fol. 62</item>
                     <item>Of the loſſe of Frendes. Fol. 63</item>
                     <item>Of impriſonment. Fol. 64</item>
                     <item>Of Exile. Fol. 66</item>
                     <item>Of Pouertie. Fol. 68</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to bewaile or lament for diuers cauſes. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>For the death of our Fren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>For things done vnto v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0</item>
                     <item>Of times. Fol. 71</item>
                     <item>Of Fortune. Fol. 72</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to demaund, or requeſt, vpon ſundrie occaſions. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>For ayde. Fol. 73</item>
                     <item>For fauour or grace. Fol. 73</item>
                     <item>For counſell. Fol. 74</item>
                     <item>For Pardon. Fol. 75</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to exhort, to ſundry purpoſes. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>TO the feare of God. Fol. 74</item>
                     <item>To liue well. Fol. 76</item>
                     <item>Vnto vertue. Fol. 77</item>
                     <item>To the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Prince. Fol. 78</item>
                     <item>To the obedience of elders, and Parents. Fol. 79</item>
                     <item>To fauour the common weale. Fol. 80</item>
                     <item>To conſtancie. Fol. 81</item>
                     <item>To patience. Fol. 82</item>
                     <item>To gratefulneſſe. Fol. 84</item>
                     <item>To louing kindneſſe. Fol. 84</item>
                     <item>To the good education of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                     <item>To flye ſlouth. Fol. 85</item>
                     <item>To ſtudie. Fol. 86</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to parle or deſcant, diuers and ſundry wayes. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>With Pleaſaunt ſpeeches. Fol. 87</item>
                     <item>With Graue ſentences. Fol. 88</item>
                     <item>With ſubtill and wittie Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. Fol. 89</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>¶ How to giue thankes, for ſundrie occaſions. Vz.
<list>
                     <item>FOr goodwill ſhewed. Fol. 90</item>
                     <item>For benefites receiued. Fol. 91</item>
                     <item>For fauour receiued. Fol. 92</item>
                     <item>For commendations receiued. Fol. 93</item>
                     <item>For being aduertiſed. Fol. 94</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9054:52"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
